<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Banners of love displaied over the Church of Christ, walking in the order of the Gospel at Hexham: by the out-stretched arm of the King of Saints, against the jesuitical design lately attempted by the false Iew. Or, An answer to a narrative stuff'd with untruths, by four Newcastle gentlemen.</title>
            <author>Tillam, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E726_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865893</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865893</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E726[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Banners of love displaied over the Church of Christ, walking in the order of the Gospel at Hexham: by the out-stretched arm of the King of Saints, against the jesuitical design lately attempted by the false Iew. Or, An answer to a narrative stuff'd with untruths, by four Newcastle gentlemen.</title>
                  <author>Tillam, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hen. Hills, and are to be sold at his house at the sign of Sir John Old Castle in Py-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 16 1653"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jews --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118147:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BANNERS of LOVE Diſplaied over the Church of Chriſt, walking in the Order of the Goſpel at HEXHAM: By the out-ſtretched Arm of the King of Saints, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuitical Deſign lately attempted by the falſe IEW. OR, An Anſwer to a Narrative ſtuff'd with Untruths, by four <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> GENTLEMEN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And the Lord will create upon every dwelling place of <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> and upon her aſſemblies, a Cloud by day, and the ſhining of a flaming fire by night: for upon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 54.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>No weapon that is formed againſt thee ſhall proſper; and every tongue that ſhall riſe againſt thee in judgement, thou ſhalt condemn.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REV. 2.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them lyars.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Hen. Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe at the ſign of <hi>Sir John Old Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Py-Corner,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118147:2"/>
            <head>To the Church of Chriſt walking in the Order of the Goſpel at HEXHAM.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY DEARLY BELOVED,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Crown of my rejoicing in Chriſt, through whom he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to convey divine conſolations, for the ſweet refreſhing of my weather-beaten ſoul, ſurrounded with storms on every hand; from <hi>Rome,</hi> from the World, and (which is most ſad) from my late fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friends, the profeſſed ſervants of the ſame God whom we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore. O my Beloved, what meaſure have you and I met with, from unreaſonable and wicked men, ſince, by a ſeparation from the world, we made a viſible profeſſion of the faith of the Goſpel? You know the many plotted lies that have been invented, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Satan and his children, That there were <hi>12</hi> perſons to be baptized at <hi>Naward</hi> Caſtle, whom I called my Apostles, and ſaid that I was their God; That I have taken <hi>12.14.20.</hi> a perſon for baptizing them; That ſome have ſeen me drunk on the Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; That I robbed a man neer unto <hi>Corbridge;</hi> That I was ſent for to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and ſo to <hi>London,</hi> to ſuffer; That ſome whom I baptized, preſently run mad, had the Palſie, were blind, have been drowned, have hanged themſelves, and many ſuch like untruths: But,
<note place="margin">Deut. 33.16. Iſa. 43.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>through the good will of him that dwelt in the Buſh,</hi> you have been preſerved in the midſt of theſe flames, ſo that from the firſt day until now, you have been living Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his unſpeakable mercy, not a hair of any of your heads periſhed; being <hi>more than conquerours through him that loveth us;</hi> his banners of l ve have been continually over us; he hath drawn out the hearts and affections of his Churches to own you; their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſpiritual Epiſtles (from <hi>London, Lempſter, Leith, Stokeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Lancaſhire,</hi> and <hi>Cheſhire</hi>) have raiſed and exceedingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed your ſpirits; and the Lord return ſeven fold into the boſoms of thoſe precious ones. O what a rich ſtock of prayers have you go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? a mighty interest in the Churches of Chriſt, who <hi>are terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:118147:3"/>as an Army with Banners.</hi> The late Jeſuitical attempt to ruin you, Chriſt diſcovered ſeaſonably, and blasted the Adverſary, yea, and turned it to your ſingular advantage, and wonderful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in number and grace; who could imagine that ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſouls ſhould be added to the Church of <hi>Hexham</hi> upon this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the <hi>Impoſtor?</hi> most men thought it would have been your ruin: but as (upon the diſcovery of thoſe grand Hypocrites) in the firſt pure Church;
<note place="margin">Acts 5.14.</note> ſo hath the Almighty bleſſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered you. But now alas your flouriſhing condition hath (I fear) stirred up a ſpirit of emulation, in thoſe congregations that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from your judgement; who under a pretence of publiſhing the falſe <hi>Jew,</hi> have mightily laboured in his deſign, to ſupplant you, who being but a young Vine, and of tender Grapes, had more need of careful dreſſing, and constant dews of conſolation, and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, than ſuch diſcouragements and defamations; as that you readily imbrace any (whether Sheep or Goats) if they be but of your opinion in Baptiſm, that you (even the whole Congregation) are given up of God to believe lies. Theſe, and ſuch like aſperſions are ſad and grievous, eſpecially from thoſe who have pretended to build with you, giving a ſecret ſtab (as it were) in the midſt of a brotherly ſalute; but tis your mercy that Chriſt deals better, cheriſhing your ſouls with his most ſweet and chaſte imbraces, as his moſt loving faithful Spouſe, carrying you in his bleſſed Arms, and folding you in his boſome of love <hi>(that Neſt and Hive of ſweetneſs)</hi> taking all your reproaches, affronts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, as done unto himſelf, <hi>while he leads you through the green Paſtures, and feeds you with marrow full of fatneſs, by the ſtill waters, hiding you in his Pavilion, and in the ſecret of his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle from the ſtrife of tongues:</hi> thus the <hi>Eternal God is your refuge, and underneath are the Everlaſting Arms.</hi> Wherefore be incouraged in the Lord, ye children of the moſt High, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what I have ſometimes taught you, <hi>That the Saints trials ſhall end in triumph, your Night of Miſery will have a moſt glorious Morning of Victory:</hi> And though it be ſad to ſuffer by Profeſſors, yet conſider, that Chriſt ſuffered by his own profeſſed people, ſo did <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 21.20 with 28.</note> and other pretious Saints. Did you ever hear of a Church increaſing, as God increaſeth you, without great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſecutions? Do not conſult with fleſh and blood, but behold the works and wonders of the Lord, how he baffles the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb facs="tcp:118147:3"/>conceits of men. Remember what a ſignal token of divine approbation was ſhewed but a moneth ſince at <hi>Muggleſwick,</hi> in the cheerful ſubmiſſion of many pretious ſouls to your despiſed Ordinance of Baptiſm (the very ſame day that it was cryed down by a <hi>Boanargis,</hi> who ſoon fell ſick, and ſo dyed) the whole night following being ſpent in Prayer, and declaring the work of grace upon their ſouls <hi>(a Vigil to be obſerved)</hi> and in the morning bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Chriſt in Baptiſm. Some of you have been ſecretly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and marvellouſly convinced of Diſciple-baptiſm onely, while you have been under the preaching of Infant-ſpringling. Live up to theſe mercies, you pretious Saints; let your holy, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble walking crown Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 Peter 2.12.</note> and more and more confute the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. <hi>So ſtand faſt in the Lord, my dearly beloved: And the God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi> You,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.1. Rom. 16.20.</note> whoſe prayers prevailed for my life, from a late extreme ſickneſs, would ſurely have me live; Why <hi>now I live,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.8. 2 Cor. 11.2.</note> if you ſtand faſt in the Lord, I have eſpouſed you to one Husband.</hi> O my deareſt, let your ſhining converſation ſo adorn your profeſſion, that I may give up my account with joy, and preſent you as <hi>a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt,</hi> when tranſported on Angels wings to the Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, we ſhall be lovingly received into our Masters joy, with <hi>Well done,</hi> and <hi>Well come.</hi> This is the life, the joy, the hope of him, who intirely and unfeignedly loves you,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Hexham <date>
                           <hi>6<hi rend="sup">mon.</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">day</hi>. 1653.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your ſervant for Jeſus ſake, to live and dy with you, THO. TILLAM.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <q rend="inline">Hear the Word of the Lord ye that tremble at his Word, your Brethren that hated you, that caſt you out for my names ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified; but he ſhall appear to your joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed.</q>
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.5.</note>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118147:4"/>
            <p>THe late Act for ejecting Popiſh Prieſts, cauſing a retreat to <hi>Rome,</hi> hath ſo enraged thoſe Locuſts, that they have invented new and unheard-of ſtratagems, to deſtroy our Vines, by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cut out and fitted for any kind of miſchief, with Unction and Benediction from the Pope, to undermine, poiſon, and bring to ruin the Churches of Chriſt. Amongſt theſe Miſcreants (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many are ſaid to be ſent into <hi>England</hi>) one ſubtil inſtrument of Satan is deſigned for <hi>Hexham</hi> in <hi>Northumberland</hi> (a place ſwarming with Papiſts) there to carry on his Plot for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Baptized Church; ſuch Churches being the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of the man of ſin, overturning his great Idol, wherewith he in churches the world in their infancy, to prevent the rejecting of his abominations when they ſhall be able to diſcover him. This wretched Emiſſary (with plenary indulgence) lands at <hi>Newcastle,</hi> and as a poor Scholar craves relief of a Miniſter there; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charity cold, he haſtens to Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Paul Hobſon,</hi> where he finds courteſie as large as report. A while after he gives it out that he is a Jew (having been circumciſed at <hi>Rome</hi> on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deceive) by the name of <hi>Ioſephus Ben Iſrael</hi> (rather <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Ben Belial</hi>) having obtained the love and letter of the Lieut. Collonel, he came to <hi>Hexham,</hi> where he acted his part ſo neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and counterfeited the convert ſo Saint-like, that after a ſolemn publick Confeſſion, he was Baptized: but within a week after his lies came to our ear (a ſeaſonable mercy to prevent his communion with the Church) which drew him to <hi>Newcastle</hi> to vindicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which with much confidence he boaſted: but God, the great preſerver of his Saints, diſcovered his hypocriſie at length, to whom be everlaſting praiſe. Hereupon four <hi>Newcastle</hi> Gent. publiſh this falſe Jew to the world, but drive on ſecretly his deſign to break the Church of <hi>Hexham,</hi> by reproaches, ſcandals, and very great untruths, to which I ſhall, in the ſtrength of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn a ſober, Chriſtian anſwer, as becommeth my profeſſion, not rendring reviling for reviling. The Gent. who have three or four times ſubſcribed it are, <hi>Tho. Weld, Cuth. Sidenham, Sam. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Will. Durant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118147:4"/>
            <p>IN their Title Page they preſent the world with a <hi>Scot,</hi> baptized at <hi>London,</hi> and rebaptized at <hi>Hexham;</hi> but we deny his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptization at <hi>Hexham,</hi> and do conceive he was only ſprinkled at <hi>London</hi> (as the manner is) and not baptized; for though much time and ſtrength was ſpent by a Gent. in <hi>Hexham</hi> Pulpit (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the great point, who were fit ſubjects for Baptiſm) to ſhew that the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> might as well be taken for ſprinkling, as dipping; yet (ſince theſe Gent. declare, my acquaintance is not great with the Rabbies) let a worthy man of their own judgement inform them, That the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Leigh Crit. Sacr.</note> ſignifieth pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, ſuch a kind of waſhing as is uſed in Bucks, where Linen is plunged, or dipt, and that the native and proper ſignification of it, is to dip into or plunge under water; for which he quotes theſe Scriptures: and in his Annotations upon <hi>Romans</hi> 6 4 he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.22, 23 Mat. 3 11, 16. Acts 8 38. Baxt. Bapt. p. 136.</note> That the manner of Baptiſm then, was to ſtrip them naked, and plunge them in the water (but this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> will ſay is a breach of the ſeventh Commandment.) And upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize,</hi> that is (ſaith he) <hi>drown you all over.</hi> Now why ſhould not we rather practiſe according to the way of the Apoſtles bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and the genuine ſignification of the word, than the Popes way of ſprinkling? but of this more at a fitter opportunity: this may ſuffice to ſhew the Gents. miſtake in the front of their falſe Jew, who was not rebaptized at <hi>Hexham;</hi> as alſo themſelves acknowledge a little after in the ſame Title Page (but that he was baptized there) but it was (ſay they) ſoon (and page 3.) very ſoon after his Landing; how ſoon it was themſelves declare, <hi>April</hi> the 21. he landed, and <hi>June the</hi> 5. he was baptized, which I am perſwaded was more time than was taken to baptize <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra, Simon Magus,</hi> and other Hypocrites, by men of more diſcerning ſpirits, than any of us. But ſurely theſe Gent. begin to ſhew an ungoſpel-like ſpirit ſoon, yea very ſoon, even in the Front of their falſe Jew; it were the eaſier born, if it did not breath wholly throughout their Narrative. But to their firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where I ſhall obſerve little, the ſtroak of death having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the Gent. to whom it was dedicated. Secondly, they mention <hi>Everard</hi> in the ſame Epiſtle (reflecting as I conceive upon us) whoſe Errours we diſown; although, through mercy, we had neither hand nor heart in that Perſecuting Petition, which theſe very Gent. preſented againſt him to his Excellency; but ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118147:5"/>be our gracious God for raiſing ſuch an eminent inſtrumental Saviour, as our Victorious and moſt renowned General, whoſe car was, is, and I hope ever will be deaf to ſuch deſires, and long may this Chriſt-like Goſpel-ſpirit ſit in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> to judge the Mount of <hi>Eſau,</hi> while all ſuch Perſecutors ſpeed like theſe Gent. in that Petition. Will not the Word, without the Sword, confute Errours? Muſt this Prelatical ſpirit ſtill be up? I perceive <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi>'s Antidote wanted ſtrength. But I go on to their ſecond Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where they ſhew Satans chief waies of deluſions; As firſt, <hi>The opening of a wide door to let in Sheep and Goats—and doth not Satan drive on ſuch an interest in the Adminiſtrators Societie, to get a number to glorie in? Anſw.</hi> Tis too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that Satan drives on a notable deſign of bitterneſs, wrath, ſtrife, and ſcandal in theſe Gents. writings. 2. A number to glory in,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, with 1 Theſ. 2.19, 20.</note> if they be gratious ones, is truly Apoſtolical; and my hope is, that the number which our gratious God is pleaſed to add dayly to the Church of <hi>Hexham,</hi> will ſo adorn their holy Profeſſion, that it ſhall be known the Gent. have reproached the Servants of the living God, Satan driving on no ſuch deſign in the Adminiſtrators Society. 3. The door was wider at <hi>Weremouth</hi> but a few months ſince, than it is, or ever will be in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators ſociety; that Pariſh way of ſprinkling is now drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a narrower compaſs; for ſince an addition of Tyths was not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, one of theſe Gent. changeth his habitation (to a warmer Quarter) and withal changeth his judgement, and as I hear, keeps the door cloſer at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> admitting no more upon a Pariſh account. But I deſire theſe Gent. to reſolve me in their next, whether only Children of Church-members have right to baptiſm? if ſo, how were the members themſelves baptized, whoſe Parents never were in ſuch Church-fellowſhip? or if all Children have right to baptiſm, how will theſe Gent. anſwer the wrong in rejecting them from that holy ordinance, expoſing them to the greedineſs of ſuch ravenous hirelings, who have been caſt out of the Miniſtery, as wolves, dumb doggs, and abominably profane wretches? If God drives on the preſent intereſt at <hi>Newca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> who did drive on the former intereſt at <hi>Weremouth?</hi> But the next paſſage in the Gents. Epiſtle will evidently point out, where Satan (the father of lyes, and the accuſer of the Brethren) drives on his intereſt; for theſe Gent. confidently declare that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118147:5"/>the letting in of the falſe Jew, <hi>the Administrator knew of his many plotted lyes.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>1</label> I muſt take up the complaint of the abuſed Prophet <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3, 4, 5. and ſpread this falſe accuſation before the juſt and righteous God, as alſo I have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> another groſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, affirmed by one of theſe Gent. in a th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g of people, <hi>viz. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>2</label> That I had neglected to preach the fund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>al truths of the everlaſting Goſpel, and had made it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>neſs to preach up Baptiſm ever ſince I came to</hi> Hexham. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> notorious falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was then detected, and ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfuted under the hand of a Parliament man, who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of about three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Sermons, (and not one of Baptiſm) the heads whereof, at our next diſpute, I produced with this atteſtation; <hi>I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared this Paper with my own Notes, and they are both one; this I thought good to certifie under my hand, very well knowing that many asperſions have been raiſed againſt Mr.</hi> Tillam, <hi>and falſe informations given in against him, which he is no way guilty of,</hi> W.F. But although full evidence declared manifeſtly the Gents. guilt in this groſs untruth, and great ſcandal, yet I never ſaw, nor heard of any repentance, but rather a ſmothering of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs by thoſe with whom he hath fellowſhip, who have alſo brought upon themſelves further guilt, by joining together in this palpable untruth, <hi>that I knew before of the Jews plotted lyes,</hi> which I am ready to diſprove by ſcores of witneſſes.
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 29.10.</note> But ſince ſuch groſs ſcales of prejudice and falſehood have ſo manifeſtly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their eyes with darkneſs that may be felt, I do the leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their following ſcornful queſtion, <hi>Whether I would baptize a man with the French Pox on his Noſe, that had committed Adultery the night before, if he did but profeſs the faith of the Goſpel, and deſire admiſſion? Anſw.</hi> I look at covetouſneſs with as hateful an eye, as either of theſe; and if ſome of theſe Gent.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> were not generally known and talked of for this kind of Idolatry, which is the root of all evil, I ſhould not have publiſhed it; but this may work their repentance. 2. I muſt freely declare, and let all the Saints know it, and well weigh it, That if a Jaylor ſhould preſently come from tormenting the tender Lambs of Chriſt, or a <hi>Simon</hi> from his Sorceries (which are worſe than the French Pox or Adultery) after I had ſhewed them the Pattern, Forms, and Ordinances of the Goſpel-Temple, and put them upon conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what it would coſt them to be Chriſtians, if they ſhould profeſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118147:6"/>the Faith of the Goſpel, with Evangelical repentance, and an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of the Ordinance; I would in the ſtrength of Chriſt ſpeedily baptize them, though it were the ſame <hi>hour of the Night;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 16.35.</note> and thus wide will I endeavour to keep the door, not an inch narrower, after the <hi>New England</hi> way, nor a foot wider to let in children, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om no Faith, Repentance, or deſire at all appears: and as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pen a door of admiſſion, ſo ſhall I as readily ſet open the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ejection, as need ſhall require, and hereby enjoy peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lgrimage, and a plain rule to make my account by in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken to their firſt way of Satans deluſions, I ſhall only ſay this to their ſecond <hi>(of undermining Churches by cloſing with Errours)</hi> That if baptizing of profeſſed Diſciples be indeed an Error, then Popiſh ſprinkling of Infants may the better paſs for a Goſpel truth; and ſo paſs to their third way of Satan, that is, <hi>To lay the main weight upon ſome particular Ordinance,</hi> which let me tell my brethren, they may not venture their ſouls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I have ſometimes told them, that it is not enough to have a Levite in our houſe, a poor prop to be only baptized, and in Church-communion, <hi>Friend how cameſt thou hither, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on a wedding Garment,</hi> will ſtartle all; <hi>therefore leaving the principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, let all ſincere ſouls go on to perfection;</hi> and as he that hath called you is holy, <hi>ſo be ye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all manner of converſation;</hi> be ſure your communion flow from a cleer union with Chriſt: what a mercy is it that the Gent. can thus far accord with us? Really Reader (thou that art the child of peace, and canſt not endure any kind of harſhneſs) it is the grief of my ſoul that I am conſtrained to dip my Pen in Vinegar at any time; but known ſins muſt have ſharp and publique reproof: I am troubled to uſe ſuch terms, as <hi>ly, untruth, falſhcod, &amp;c.</hi> but I have profeſſed (though it procure a jeer from the Gent.) not to daub with untempered Morter.
<note place="margin">Lev. 19.17. Jer. 1.17, 18. 1 Tim. 5.20, 21. Tit. 1.12, 13.</note> And if thou well weigh theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, thou wilt find it a duty both to me and thy ſelf, wherefore I deſire thee peruſe them.</p>
            <p>But though we can heartily cloſe with theſe Gent. in their third particular; yet in that wherewith they cloſe their Epiſtle we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; for it is a groſs untruth, to cloſe the Jews Declararation about Church Communion at the end of ſeven lines, with <hi>Caetera deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (<hi>id est,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth </seg>3</label> the reſt is wanting) for the Gent. had full two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118147:6"/>pages more in their hand of that they call the Jews argument for Baptiſm: And to this groſs untruth they add another (a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy act) in printing my Animadverſions upon the whole, when the one half of the Jew was not printed; and then tell the Reader, <hi>That they were my own conceptions, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>4</label> and not bottomed upon the Confeſſion;</hi> which I muſt tell the Gent. is another untruth, as the Reader ſhall ſee upon peruſual of the whole. No wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they ſhould be ſtrongly deluded to believe his lyes, whom they knew to be a Lyar. He told them (and it ſeems they believe it) <hi>that he forged Authors for the ſtrengthning us in our opinion.</hi> Reader, haſt thou one Beam of light? I will appeal to thy Conſcience, Canſt thou imagine that the Popes deſign is to ſtrengthen us in our opinion of baptizing Diſciples only, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching down his Infant ſprinkling, which ſhakes his ſeat, and makes his Tripple Crown to totter, unchurching all whom his ſprinkling Idol hath churched? No, no, his very ſoul abhors it, and therefore he it ſeems annointed and appointed this accurſed Impoſtor to undermine and ruine us; but the mighty Arm of Chriſt our King, hath wonderfully detected, and defeated the ſtratagem, and ſecured his poor profeſſed deſpiſed ſervants, from the malice and ſubtilty of Satan, Antichriſt, the World, and all falſe Brethren. O that we may walk worthy of this mercy to his praiſe! Thus much to the Gents. Epiſtle; They have alſo an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction mentioning <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat.</hi> And many ſuch we have met with while this Goſpel-Church hath been building, who have endeavoured to weaken our hands from the work; but theſe Gent. outſtrip all. They cloſe the introduction, with telling the world, That <hi>the Administrator and his Society gloried much in this new Convert. Anſw.</hi> He ſeemed to us a real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and therefore we did but our duty in rejoicing, as Angels,
<note place="margin">Luke 15.10. Acts 8.8.</note> do; and as Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> with his Society would (and ought to do) have done, yea, and as one of his Society did, who was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded alſo by him, more than my ſelf; I being deceived before his lies came to my ear; but ſo neatly and ſubtilly did he diſſemble that he deceived this Gent. after he had heard of his lies: for ſo Saint-like were all his anſwers, that they well deſerved all that the Gent. hath reported to the world in his <hi>Counterfeit Jew,</hi> that is, <hi>Orthodox, Spiritual, Learned, Practical.</hi> I ſhall now take a view of the Gents. <hi>Narrative,</hi> where the forementioned
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118147:7"/>Member, in Fellowſhip with Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> is honoured with the Title of their <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> although they confeſs <hi>he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by the falſe Jew;</hi> but when afterward he appears on the Adminiſtrators part, againſt their ungoſpel-like carriage, then the Gentlemen are pleaſed to term him a <hi>Stickler,</hi> and his plea, <hi>A perillous Argument.</hi> I might upon handſomer grounds deride the conceit in Mr. <hi>Shadforths</hi> examination, as a frothy and idle fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; namely, <hi>That it is the Popes project to bring People in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o a Congregation, or Church, and after to Anabaptiſm—which was as much as they ſought after, and all they deſired.</hi> Is it poſſible that theſe Gent. ſhould be ſo over-credulous, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there is any truth at all in this whimſey? they have been at it before,
<note place="margin">Page 5.</note> and I have anſwered it. But howſoever theſe Gent. deal with me, yet I hope prejudice ſhall never ſo far cover the eyes of my underſtanding as to think that the Pope deſires to draw people into Congregational Churches: but I muſt confeſs this is as likely as that which ſome with much confidence affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> That the deſign of the Anabaptiſts is to draw people to Popery; yet poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Pope may have entertained Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> conceit, That our way of baptizing will ſhorten the Peoples lives, and <hi>that it is good for nothing but to diſpatch men out of the world,
<note place="margin">Bax. Bap. pag. 135.</note> and to ranken Church-yards;</hi> and upon this occount indeed he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to draw people to Anabaptiſm. But if M. <hi>Baxters</hi> judgement be right herein, what need he and others be ſo hot in diſpute and perſecution, let them have but a little patience and our practice will deſtroy our ſelves: but doubtleſs ſuch will prove falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 44.25.</note> and the gratious promiſe of the King of Saints, will fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the expectation of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and his Complices, who conſult only with fleſh and blood, and are more in love with their eaſe, than Chriſts Ordinance, not daring to expoſe themſelves to the danger and reproach of the Water (in <hi>Philips</hi> way <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38.) eſpecially in cold Regions and ſeaſons; there is danger of many mortal diſeaſes, Catarrhs, &amp;c. ſaies Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> in the eye of reaſon I grant, but a promiſe of divine aſſiſtance in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Lo I am with you alway, even to the end of the world,</hi> carries the obedient ſoul upon the wings of an active faith, through all dangers, difficulties, and diſgraces. Bleſſed inſtances of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly aid in this undertaking, might be produced to confute the Adverſary; many tender, ſickly perſons, ſome very great with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118147:7"/>Child (let Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> make himſelf ſport with it if he will) ſome of great eminency,
<note place="margin">As in his Bap. pag. 136.</note> in cold ſeaſons have valiantly followed Chriſt through this part of righteouſneſs; neither did I ever know any that ſuffered by it. And though it be cenſured for an imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent digreſſion, yet ſince the Adminiſtrator is the But, and Baptiſm is Mark the Gent. chiefly aim at, I ſhall fully anſwer to Mr. <hi>Shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forths</hi> conceit, in declaring. That if this be the Popes deſign in drawing People to Anabaptiſm, he will be as much miſtaken as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is. Catarrhs are not generated, but through a ſecret bleſſing rather profligated by this practice of Baptiſm. The Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator upon his firſt undertaking, had a ſharp Catarrh, and was greatly diſtempered, the ſeaſon cold, the Perſons baptized many, but through mercy his Catarrh vaniſhed. My Reverend Brother Mr. <hi>Will. Kaye</hi> (who by his Miniſtry gathered a people at <hi>Stokeſly</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi>) after long communion in the way called <hi>Independent,</hi> was convinced of Baptiſm: after which he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to convince many, and in the midſt of a ſharp diſtillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Rheume, did very much honour Chriſt by a late cheerful ſubmiſſion (and many pretious ſouls with him) to the holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſm, and was preſently raiſed, ſtrengthned, elevated, to our great admiration, having ſince baptized many without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Therefore let not his Holineſs, nor any of his Adherents, dream of drawing people this way to deſtruction. But enough hath been ſaid to Mr. <hi>Shadforths</hi> examination, and I muſt now anſwer the Gents. charge againſt the Adminiſtrator. <hi>Who was not afraid to compare the</hi> Jews <hi>lies to</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Davids <hi>ſins, but owned him as an Angel of God, and his Dear Brother in Christ. Anſw.</hi> I muſt confeſs that the harſh and High Commiſſion like dealing of theſe Gent. (which tended not, neither did God own, as to a diſcovery) conſtrained me the more to appear for him, while I thought him innocent, and could ſee nothing at all proved againſt him, which was neither vain-glorious, nor affronting, as they pleaſe to term it. And for comparing him to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> I ſuppoſe I might warrantably do it, when with <hi>David,</hi> I heard him cry out lamentably, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> with teares and trembling, profeſſing a loathing and deteſtation of his former ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations. But to proceed, the next charge is. <hi>That the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrator affirmed that many of the</hi> Jews <hi>could ſpeak perfect</hi> Engliſh. <hi>Anſw.</hi> They cannot charge me with ſpeaking untruth:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118147:8"/>I ſuppoſe none will deny, but a Jew trained from his in fancy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Engliſh (as many of them are) may ſpeak as perfect Engliſh, as a <hi>Scot</hi> may do <hi>Hebrew,</hi> which they confeſs this <hi>Scot</hi> could do, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>line</hi> 18. and the <hi>Counterfeit Jew, pag.</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 9. but this charge is only as lightning to the enſuing thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for if my life, liberty, credit, or whatſoever is dear, lay at ſtake, the Gent. have proclaimed it to the world, that <hi>ſome yeers ſince the Adminiſtrator was a Papiſt;</hi> I leave the Saints to corſider from what kind of Spirit this proceeds. It was with much Prelatical, High Commiſſion-like Lordlineſs lately deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a throng of People, by one (and I think the youngeſt) of theſe Gent. if I had not been a Papiſt? I durſt not then deny what now I declare to the world, That about twenty years ſince my poor ſoul was deluded by Antichriſt; and through infinite riches of grace, the everlaſting bonds of diſtinguiſhing love drew me out of that horrible Pit 17. years ſince, which the Gent. would not declare, but mention ſome years ſince, as though it were but lately that I was a Papiſt: thus all the dirt they can poſſibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, raking <hi>Romes</hi> filthy ditch and all, they freely caſt in my face: But if I ſhould declare what I have heard, and can prove of ſome of theſe Gent. 17. years ſince, it would much diſpleaſe. And now that they have thus laboured to cover me with ſhame and diſgrace, they leave me a little for the world to gaze on, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving endeavoured to make me many foes, they are troubled that I ſhould have any friends, wherefore he who but lately was their dear friend, they muſt now contend with (for appearing on my part, againſt their fierce and bitter actings) he confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed (as they ſay) <hi>That becauſe the</hi> Jews <hi>could pronounce</hi> Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>therefore they could ſpeak perfect Engliſh,</hi> which creates this ſcoff (which their friend muſt wear as a favour from them) <hi>A porilous argument.</hi> No wonder I ſhould be thus laden with reproaches, ſcorns and ſlanders, when their dear friend cannot eſcape them: but the truth was this, the Gent. judging improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (or impoſſible) that a Jew ſhould ſpeak ſo good Engliſh, preſented a <hi>Dutch Schoolmaster,</hi> who could not ſpeak plain Engliſh, as an Argument to prove that no <hi>Jews</hi> could ſpeak our Language perfectly; ſo that here lay their ſtrength, <hi>This Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man cannot ſpeak perfect Engliſh, therefore no Jew can ſpeak perfect Engliſh:</hi> ſo that juſtly is their jeer retorted in their own
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118147:8"/>Dialect—<hi>A perilous Argument.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See pag. 13.</note> It was his Argument that occaſioned the Speech of their dear friend, That <hi>ſome Jews had more command of their Organs, with volubility of expreſſion, than Germans,</hi> and gave this inſtance of <hi>Shibboleth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 12.6.</note> From deriding their dear Friend, the Gent. fall upon Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> for no other fault that I know of, but that he is alſo againſt the ſprinkling of infants, and gave more Biſhop-like entertainment than any of themſelves; and yet they ſay,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>That he was courteouſly entertained, and particularly by one of them;</hi> but what this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment was, you may perceive by the Jews plea for leaving <hi>Newcastle</hi> ſo ſoon; namely, <hi>becauſe he could get no lodging,</hi> ſo that here is the latitude of theſe Gents, courteſie, which is thus publiſhed in print: Had an Antipaedobaptiſt boaſted of ſo ſmall a piece of Charity, as would not amount to a Nights Lodging, it would have been cenſured for the ſounding of a Phariſaical Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; a little of theſe Gents. Charity goes far. But now the Gent. declare another grievous crime of the Lieutenant Collonel, <hi>For the Jew</hi> (ſay they) <hi>acknowledged that he had heard much of the Lieutenant Collonel at</hi> Rome. Believe it, <hi>A perillous Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The Lieutenant Collonel hath been talked of at <hi>Rome. Ergo</hi>—Tis like that by this time ſome of theſe Gent. are alſo ſpoken of at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince they have appeared in Print pleading for ſprinkling (the Popes <hi>Diana,</hi> and the beſt market of the hireling exploded Prieſt) and doubtleſs the preaching and printing of the Lieutenant Collonel, with his late Publique employment in the Government of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> hath been heard of in other places beſides <hi>Rome.</hi> What ſtrange ſuſpitious inſinuations are theſe? The Adminiſtrator hath been a Papiſt <hi>ſome years ſince,</hi> and the Lieutenant Collonel <hi>hath been heard of at</hi> Rome: The Gent. are loath it ſeems to ſpeak all out, we may both poſſibly have a moneths mind to <hi>Rome</hi> yet. O enmity, prejudice, emulation, falſehood, whither do you mean to tranſport theſe Gent.? This poſſeſſeth the rude multitude, that we are certainly Papiſts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving by <hi>baptizing</hi> Diſciples to turn all to Popery; whereupon they invent lies, and ſince theſe Gent. put forth their falſe Jew) make Libels, and violently aſſault me in my own houſe. Thus the Gent. having repreſented us ſuſpitious to the world, Declare, That after the Jew had lived about a moneth with the Lieurenant Collonel, he commended him to the Adminiſtrator at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118147:9"/>which as theſe Gent. would inſinuate, <hi>is the commendation of one Popiſhly affected to another. Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Jew</hi> indeed brought me a Letter from the Li. Col. wherin the moſt concernd the Jew was, <hi>That the Ministers of Newcaſtle are diſcontented at him, and ſome of them ſay he is no Scholar, which I do not believe: I am ſure his condition calls for love and pitty:</hi> but let the Reader take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That the Gent. of <hi>Newcastle</hi> are now in another mind, and do confeſs he is a great Scholar, in their falſe Jew, <hi>page</hi> 12. <hi>line</hi> 18. So that you ſee theſe Gent. are not infallible in their judgements, and can no more know the ſecrets of a heart than the depths of a Scholar, till full fruits appear. Having let fly two or three Arrowes at Rovers againſt their dear Friend, and the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel, they return with a full Quiver to their conſtant But.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ. pag. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Administrator baptized him within a few daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came to</hi> Hexham. <hi>The Administrator ſtill with much confidence affimed him to be a</hi> Jew. <hi>The Administrator preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly replyed for him. The Administrator told us very angerly, that he ſaw bitterneſs of ſoul and brokenneſs of heart in him for thoſe lies, which we did not chriſtianly to preſs. The Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strator called him an Angel of God.</hi> What is all this, but now have at the Adminiſtrator, have at the Adminiſtrator? lets ſmite him, wound, break, blaſt him to purpoſe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator had as much ground to conclude he was a Jew, as <hi>Philip</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> to judge <hi>Simon Magus</hi> or <hi>Ananias</hi> Believers:
<note place="margin">Luke 6.44.</note> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this confidence (by a ſure rule) the Adminiſtrator looked upon it as his duty to baptize him, and to plead for him againſt that high Commiſſion courſe that was taken, but not bleſſed of God to detect him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>6</label> But it is an untruth to ſay, <hi>I called him an Angel of God:</hi> I wiſhed them to mitigate that rigorous, fierce carriage, and be more civil, courteous and chriſtian to Strangers, ſince ſome had entertained Angels thereby unawares, which he might poſſibly prove,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.2.</note> ſince all their fierceneſs could find nothing at all of proof againſt him: indeed, when I heard him ſay, That <hi>ſuch hard uſage was enough to cauſe him to go back to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and write against Christianity,</hi> I did roundly and ſharply reprove him, and from that time ſided not with him, as ſuſpecting the frame of his ſpirit, being far from his former temper: but in this the Gent. are ſilent. Let the Reader (if he can) eſpy one good word for the Adminiſtrator throughout all the Gents. falſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118147:9"/>Iew, but all the Gall and Wormwood they can procure. When nothing could be proved againſt the Iew, being ready to depart without a diſcovery, Alderman <hi>George Dawſon</hi> offered, that if I would ſee him forthcoming, he ſhould go with me; but ſeriouſly I found my ſpirit averſe ſince his late expreſſion, when of a ſudden, after the Gents fierceneſs had done no good, the Almighty ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of hearts ordered the ſteps of a man at that inſtant into the Room with two Lecters, the one directed to <hi>Thomas Horſeley,</hi> but ſo worn, ſpelled and written, that there was much difficulty in reading of it; yet ſo much appeared, that his guilt appeared more, than by all the former rugged, unchriſtian dealing; yet ſtill he faced it out, and ſubtilly evaded all; at length I deſired that I might take him into the Garden, which was readily grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> alſo whiſpering in mine ear, <hi>to ſift him thoroughly;</hi> but this the Gent. ſmother, declaring, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>7</label> That <hi>the Iew deſired to go aſide with the Adminiſtrator:</hi> whereas God knows, and ſome of themſelves know, that the motion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was mine. What a naughty ſpirit is it that ſets theſe Gent. a work, concealing all that might render the Adminiſtrator any way acceptable, and proclaiming all that may any way tend to his diſps ragement? amongſt the reſt, declaring, <hi>that they knew not what paſſed betwixt us;</hi> which is untrue; for I declared to them, That I preſſed him with all my might, by perſwaſions, allurements, threatnings, to diſcover the particulars of that guilt I manifeſtly diſcerned in him: but before I could obtain this, ſome others came to us, which made him more reſerved, ſo that I ſet to it ſingly the ſecond time; but all the Gent. comming into the Garden much a muſed him. Then Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and ſome others laboured with him; but when they could not prevail, I was deſired the third time to try what God would do; who now ſo mightily appeared, in a corner of the Garden neer the River, that the wretch confeſſed his impoſture, telling me, that if his life might be ſecured he would make known ſtrange things; but not daring to promiſe more than I could perform, I called to Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who upon ſome promiſes and encouragements, had all diſcovered, As <hi>that he was no</hi> Iew, <hi>but, to act the Iews part, was circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at</hi> Rome. That <hi>he was Mr.</hi> Alexander Ramſey<hi>'s Son.</hi> That <hi>he would diſcover many Popiſh Plots againſt</hi> England, &amp;c. After this, Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Durant</hi> deſired me, as being beſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118147:10"/>acquainted with him, to give him ſome Chriſtian Counſel, which I willingly performed, labouring to touch, or if poſſibly, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken his ſeared conſcience, and hardned impenitent heart, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the juſt hand of a ſin-ſearching God, &amp;c. Amongſt other things, I demanded of him, <hi>How I ſhould know that he took up Baptiſm at</hi> Hexbam <hi>upon any other tearms than he took up Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion at</hi> Rome, id eſt, <hi>on purpoſe to deceive?</hi> He anſwered, That <hi>all he could ſay was his converſation while he was amongst us:</hi> And thus much for the diſcovery of the Impoſtor, with which the Gent. draw to an end of their Narrative, onely ſome paſſages it ſeems <hi>they had almost forgot;</hi> They had almoſt forgot <hi>to tearm their dear friend a Stickler,</hi> whom they ſay urged this Agument for the Counterfeit triumphingly, <hi>Did ye ever hear or read of an Emiſſary from</hi> Rome <hi>that ſubmitted to the Ordinance of Baptiſm? Anſ.</hi> I ſuppoſe that as theſe Gent. could not name one, ſo they never heard of ſuch an Impoſtor as this; the Pope, with his ſcarlet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, and ſubtil Jeſuits, and bloody Inquiſition, are now hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching new projects to undermine and ruine the true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>8</label> A ſecond paſſage which the Gent. <hi>had almoſt forgot,</hi> is a moſt notorious untruth, <hi>viz. That the Adminiſtrator called the Counterfeit to partake of the Ordinance of the Lords Supper, and that he diſſembled to avoid it.</hi> Reader, there is not one ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of truth in this almoſt forgotten paſſage; here are many living witneſſes in the Church of <hi>Hexham</hi> to teſtifie, That the falſe Jew moſt earneſtly deſired the Ordinance, and the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor (by deſire of the Church) wiſhed him to forbear until he had cleared himſelf at <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> wherupon he moſt exquiſitly acted the part of a dejected, forlorn, perplexed ſoul, ſmiting his breaſt, and with tears and trembling (for no doubt he can quake) profeſſed that his ſoul did weep, even tears of blood for thoſe lyes, which he thought no ſin when they were ſpoken. Thus the Gent-inſtead of ours, have publiſhed their own ſhame in this great falſehood; and not onely this, for the falſe Jew tells them, which being to our reproach they publiſh, <hi>That he looked upon our Baptiſm as no more than the waſhing of his hands, but for the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, that he diſſembled to avoid.</hi> But can theſe Gent. believe, that the Papiſts have any more eſteem of our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lords Supper, than of our Baptiſm? Certainly, our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118147:10"/>Communion is no leſs contrary to their Maſſe, in all particulars, than our Baptiſm to their Sprinkling. Is not the ſame judgement, which the Gent. ſay is ſeized upon us, juſtly faln upon themſelves? being given up of God <hi>to believe lies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11.</note> and that from he mouth of a known Lyar. Truly, although theſe Gent. judge nothing of God in us, yet for the honour of truth, they ſhould have enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us, being but ſixteen miles from them, before they had Publiſhed theſe groſs and ſlanderous untruths. But I proceed to their third paſſage, which was almoſt forget, The <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor thought to terrifie us, in ſaying, This Jew was ſent for into the Army. Anſ.</hi> I fear, that in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ad of this paſſage, the Gent. have almoſt forgot themſelves, in uſurping the Throne of God, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intrenching upon his Prerogative Royal; Do they know my thoughts? God alone knows the thoughts of men; How then can they ſay, The <hi>Administrator thought to terrifie us?</hi> I wiſh the Gent. who boaſt ſo much of the knowledge of the heart and thought, to read 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4, 10, 11. But why ſhould theſe Gent. be terrifyed with the Army? I know not any Profeſſors that fear the Army, but ſuch as are principled for perſecution; indeed it is thought theſe Gent. have not much affected the Army, ſince Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Everard,</hi> and his Brother, ſtirred up their ſpirits to perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a Petition, which our Noble Lord General, like an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Chriſtian, ſlighted. But the Gent. do every way abuſe me in declaring that I ſaid, The <hi>Jew was ſent for into the Army.</hi> I ſaid indeed, <hi>That the Jew was invited into</hi> Scotland <hi>by a godly tender-hearted Chriſtian, commiſerating his mean condition.</hi> Being almoſt tyred with theſe Paſſages which had been as good altogether, as almoſt forgotten, I haſten, having already an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweted to all that concerns us, in the falſe Jews Examinations; it is our great mercy that God reſtrained him from inventing lyes of us, for out it had come, we muſt have ſhared with Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hobſon,</hi> whom here the Gent. preſent to the world, from the Jows mouth, a perſon of credit, <hi>As a ſlighter of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, a neglecter of Family Duties; For,</hi> ſay they, <hi>the Jew was much preſſed by one, how he could ſtand under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Lioutenant Collone!</hi> Hoboſons <hi>pravers, being ſo long in his Family:</hi> To which he plainly anſwered, <hi>That they uſed no Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily Duties while he was there.</hi> How Goſpel-like had it been if theſe Gent. had enquired the truth, before they had thus publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118147:11"/>defamed the Lieutenant-Colonel, living but ten miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; I hope he will vindicate himſelf, and ſhew that he dare not expoſe himſelf and Family to that direful curſe,
<note place="margin">Ier 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Pour out thy fury upon the Heathen that know thee not, and upon the Families that call not on thy Name.</hi> Having thus wounded the reputation of the Lieutenaut-Colonel, they are pleaſed again to let fly at the Adminiſtrator, and his Allies, <hi>for crying up the falſe Jews Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> To which I anſwer, That if it be well weighed by the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader, as the Confeſſion of a Iew, it will appear a very full Confeſſion, <hi>of a Meſſiah come in the Fleſh.</hi> For the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have dealt moſt unworthily, in concealing that part of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, wherein much of the excellency of a work of grace (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely counterfeited by him) is contained, moſt in juriouſly brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off, with a <hi>Caetera deſiderantur.</hi> When I demanded of M. <hi>Hammond,</hi> whether he would have denied the <hi>Iew</hi> Baptiſm up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Confeſſion? He anſwered, <hi>Yes; becauſe of his many lies;</hi> But when I replyed, That his lies were unknown to me at that time; <hi>Nay then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſhould have not denyed him.</hi> And now I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Gentlemen have not forgot any one paſſage: they have let fly every way, at the Church of <hi>Hexham,</hi> at the Adminiſtrator, at their dear Friend, at the Lieutenant-Colonel, at Captain <hi>Everard,</hi> at the Army, and before they have done, My dearly beloved, and moſt cordial Fellow-Labourer, will be brought upon the Stage by them. Really, the Adminiſtrator hath as good company as he could wiſh; in this alone the Gentlemen have been courteous. 'Tis no ſmall mercy, my dear Brethren and Friends, that you and I are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name, who hath ſuffered the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrath for us;
<note place="margin">Heb. 10 32 33.</note> 'tis one Goſpel-mark of illumination, <hi>Partly whilest yee are made a gazing ſtock both by reproaches and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and partly whileſt ye became companions of them that were ſo uſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here I preſent you with the falſe</hi> Iew, <hi>truly and faithfully, as it was written with his own Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="religious_testimony">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118147:11"/>
               <head>The ſubſtance of the <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> which was made at the publike Meeting-Houſe at <hi>HEXHAM,</hi> the fourth Moneth, the fifth Day, 1653. By <hi>IOSEPH BEN ISRAEL.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 11.1.</hi>
                     </bibl> I ſay then, hath God caſt away his People? God forbid. For I alſo am an Iſraelite, of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>[Judah] Benjamin.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Men, Brethren, and Fathers,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>MY purpoſe is to declare unto this Congregation, firſt my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent and Education; and ſecondly, the great work of my Converſion.</p>
                     <p>I verily am a man which am a Iew, of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Act. 23.</note> born in <hi>Mantua,</hi> a City in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> a Province of <hi>Italy,</hi> trained up in the Religion of my Fathers, and brought up in the choiceſt learning of my Countrey, and having attained unto eight Languages, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took me ſetiouſly to the Study of Philoſophy; where meeting with <hi>Plato</hi> (ſirnamed Divine) <hi>Trinum per unum, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Hermes Triſmegistus,</hi> I found ſuch light in the glorious Myſtery of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity, that I was wonderfully ſurprized and amazed; and the more, that Heathens ſhould come to the knowledge of this moſt excellent Doctrine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Lord,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>how ſhall thoſe Philoſophers riſe in judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, who have more light, even</hi> ſepher hattorah, <hi>the Book of the Law? the former book rendred them inexcuſable, but what will become of us, who have the revealed Will of God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I had not gone three foot-ſteps in this way, but I found <hi>Elohim</hi> in the plurall number, compounded with a ſingular word <hi>Bara,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, upon which my meditation was much raiſed to admire this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie; when paſsing on a little further, I met with <hi>Nangas haadam betrolmenu,</hi> Let us perfect man with our Image. Why us? but that we ſhould underſtand the plurality holden forth in the Creator: this drew my Meditations firſt towards the Chriſtians <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> But now Satan (the profeſſed enemy of Chriſt, of al that ſet their faces towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) told me, <hi>that theſe were but fancies, and deluſions of my own brain; ſhall the Heatheniſh Philoſophers be a rule for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118147:12"/>no, I will follow the Law, under which I was born and educated.</hi> Behold the power of Satans ſnares, and behold the vileneſs of mine own heart, forſaking this bleſſed light, and reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting all theſe holy motions, returning to my former old waies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But here, through the goodneſs of God, I found no reſt, but very much trouble, and anquiſh of ſpirit: But O the loving kindneſs of God! whoſe deſign graticuſly appeared to bring me to the knowledge of himſelf, even from our own way of worſhip. Our Doctors chuſe out a place to ſay every Morning and Evening, <hi>Shemang Iſrael Adonay Eloheinu Adona echad.</hi> Hear O Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, the Lord our God, the Lord is one. Immediately upon this I find thrice, <hi>Elohenu, Jehovah, Iehovah,</hi> the Lord, &amp;c. O Brethren, I cannot expreſs the heart-ſearchings and movings that were upon me at that inſtant, which with my former Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, engaged my ſoul in a firm belief of the bleſſed Three in One, which moſt ſacred Trinity I do invocate as a witneſs of the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my heart, holding concurrence with my words. O Holy of Holies, Father, Son and Spirit, Searcher of the heart, and Tryer of the reins, be pleaſed to give ſtrength and courage to avow thee; grant that my lips may enunciate truth, and deal with thy ſervant according to the integrity of his heart.</p>
                     <p>After diligent enquiry of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I did in heart confeſs him as the moſt high God, taking upon him our nature; but then Satan ſets upon me with freſh and violent temptations, which cauſed me to break forth, <hi>O my ſoul, its for thee I care; go I back to the Law, I loſe thee, and thy caſe my body; go I forward to thoſe that profeſs this Meſſiah, and behold groſs and abominable Idolatry; look upward, and behold a just and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, the puniſher of it; look about thee, and behold all thy friends aſhamed of thee, and thy neereſt relations our ſing thee and the Meſſiah whom thou believeſt. But can this be the true Meſſiah, whoſe diſciples are ſo notoriouſly wicked, wallowing in all kind of ſin, and woful Idolatry?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the midſt of theſe perplexities and diſtractions of ſpirit, I was almoſt ſwallowed up of deſpair.</p>
                     <p>And while I thought of returning to the way of my Fathers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the holy Scriptures, I diſcovered many groſs untruths and corruptions of the Doctors; as concerning the in carnation of Chriſt, <hi>Behold a Virgin ſhall conceive and bear a Son,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſaiah 7.14.</note> they render <hi>Gnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah,</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118147:12"/>a corrupted woman (which is no ſign or wonder at all) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for a corrupted woman to conceive and bear a Son. So for the ſufferings of Chriſt, inſtead of <hi>caru,</hi> they digged, or pierced,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.16.</note> they read <hi>caari,</hi> as a Lion, that ſo they may caſt a miſt upon the true Meſſiah.</p>
                     <p>And now the good hand of Providence brought to my view the Syriack and Greek Copies of <hi>Guido Fabricius Boderianus,</hi> and by comparing theſe with the Law and the Prophets, I found all Prophecies fulfilled in Jeſus Chriſt, without contradiction, which, through the goodneſs of God, raiſed me to a full reſolution, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Satan, the enemy of my ſoul, I will delay no longer, but fly to Chriſt; come Lord, the deſire of my ſoul, lead me in the way of life.</hi> Now I reſolved to leave my Country, and Friends, and to go over the <hi>Alpes</hi> to find a people profeſſing the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> not in Legal waies, but in ſpirit and truth; for the Papiſts go on the ſame way that my own people do, altogether Legally, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> reſt on the work done, and by their horrible idolatry to Pictures and Images, are a grievous ſtumbling block unto the Jews, and were a great obſtruction to my converſion.</p>
                     <p>Coming into <hi>Germany,</hi> inſtead of finding comfort to my poor ſoul by Communion with Chriſtians in a ſpiritual way of worſhip, without human Traditions, I find their great <hi>Idol</hi> Conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many other <hi>Idols</hi> of their own inventions; this is not Chriſts way, I will not enter this way, no more of this. Lord what ſhall I do? I will not go without my buſineſs.</p>
                     <p>Away I go to <hi>Heſſen,</hi> where all are <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> here Organs, Forms, and wicked lives turned away my heart from them.</p>
                     <p>So that from <hi>Hamburg</hi> I came into <hi>England,</hi> and while I was thus ſeeking Chriſt without, in the way and order of his holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, I found him alſo within, to the exceeding joy of my ſoul. <hi>Bleſſed be thou King Jeſus, who lives in thy Saints by Faith, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating thy ſelf through thine Ordinances: thou ſhewest me my loſt eſtate in</hi> Adam, <hi>and the only way of recovery in thy ſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When we come to a ſight of our own undone condition, then we ſee the neceſſity of a Savior, and the danger of our ſouls without Chriſt, and then Chriſt lovingly cloathes the poor ſinner with the pretious Robes of his own Righteouſneſs. Fleſhly Privileges inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles none to any thing of Chriſt, <hi>Though I might, &amp;c.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See Phil. 3.4.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lord Jeſus preſent me at the day of judgement before the Father
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118147:13"/>in theſe long white Robes, I diſclaim all other coverings; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I counted gain before, I now count loſs for Chriſt, yea doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him,
<note place="margin">Phil 3.7.</note> not having mine own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>And ſince my Lord Ieſus hath appointed Ordinances for his people that have him within them enthroned in their hearts, and that I am called upon to ariſe and be baptized,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I do here avow thee Lord Ieſus my true Saviour, and I rejoyce in thy Church and People, thy precious Saints, who do here walk through thy grace, according to thy Rule and holy Commands.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I do here ſolemnly vow thee my Lord and King, thy Saints and Ordinances; and now I heartily deſire all the people of God to pray for me, that the reſidue of my days may be ſpent according to this beginning.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Lord Ieſus, who hath appointed Ordinances, and ſufferings for thoſe who ſhall reign with thee in glory, ſhew the deſire of my ſoul is to thee; do thou therefore convey the grace of Ordinances into my heart, that I may live to the honor of thy name, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thy profeſſed ſervant, waiting for thy ſecond coming. So come Lord Jeſus, and tarry not.</hi> Baruch Adonay lengolam vanged A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ve Amen.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Scripſit propria manu.</hi> R. Joſephus B. Iſrael, <hi>Heb. Mant.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I having thus, with much brevity, diſcovered the glorious work of God in my ſouls union with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I ſhall add ſomwhat more in reference to that communion with his people under which I now walk, and wherein I greatly rejoyce, That it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to all the world that my preſent actings are not bottomed upon ſelfiſh carnal principles, but upon reall and clear convictions of ſpirit.</p>
                     <p>My anſwer therefore to them that ſhall demand of me a reaſon why I entred into communion with a people who are injuriouſly termed <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> is this,</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118147:13"/>
                     <p>When firſt it pleaſed the Father of lights to ſhine into my ſoul with the lights of the glorious Goſpel of a Chriſt, he ſet my ſoul a longing to find out a people whoſe lives were ſuitable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and both conformable to the Rule of his Word.</p>
                     <p>Whiles I was thus longing, comming to <hi>Hamburg,</hi> I heard great things of Chriſtians in <hi>England.</hi> It was welcome news to me, but alas, how to attain to ſuch a people I knew not. Many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties appeared; a dangerous voyage by Sea, uncertainty of ever comming thither, by reaſon of the preſent troubles upon the Seas; and in caſe I ſhould arrive there, I knew of no liberty or protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on granted to our People in that Nation; ſo that although I might eſcape the danger of the Sea, yet I feared the Laws of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth would not ſuffer me to live, when I was come on Shore. And here my Faith fainted, ſo that unbelief prevailing upon me (being reſolved to run all hazzards, rather than fall ſhort of what I ſought for) I made a lye my refuge, and ſought ſelf-preſervation under falſhood, by denying my Nation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, and giving out my ſelf to thoſe in the ſhip with me, to be an Engliſh-man. Which failing of mine, I now bewail, and craving pardon through Chriſt, do believe I ſhall receive it at the hand of the Father, for I did it ignorantly through ſlaviſh fear and unbelief, ſuch things among the Jews being counted no ſin.</p>
                     <p>Yet the Lord, who is rich in mercy, notwithſtanding this miſ-car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, was pleaſed to bring me ſafely to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> where I heard of Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Paul Hobſon,</hi> who upon my addreſs to him, courteouſly entertained me, and ſhewed me many favors, <hi>De cujus in me humanitate mallem tacere quam pauca dicere.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>After three weeks abode with him, I deſired to ſee the order and fellowſhip of the Saints at <hi>Hexham:</hi> In anſwer to my deſires he recommended me by his Letter to the Miniſter of the Baptized Church, who, together with the whole Church, received me gladly, and in a way becoming their profeſſion.</p>
                     <p>After ſuch a people I eſpecially enquired, <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note>the Lord having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced me, that there was no way of becomming a viſible Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord Jeſus but by Baptiſm, and that Faith was neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to precede the adminiſtration of it. The Scripture through which the Lord was pleaſed to break in with a conviction in this particular upon my ſpirit, was that of <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. confirmed by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118147:14"/>the conſtant practice of the Diſciples in the Hiſtory of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; neither did I ever meet with any plain Scripture thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this light; but many concurring to confirm me in the truth I had received. So that <hi>Hic ſisto pedem,</hi> till they who walk by a rule prepoſterous to this, can ſhew me a clear and plain Scripture for ſuch their walkings. To bottom Ordinances upon mens inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, how rationally ſoever deduced, is not to me conſiſtent with the faithfulneſs of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who was the great Apoſtle and Prophet of his Church, and left not his houſhold without plain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how he would have them to go in and out before him in all wel-pleaſing, and not to depend upon the extracts of the wiſeſt of Mens Reaſonings.</p>
                     <p>For <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was but a Servant (in whoſe Houſe from my youth up I have been educated) was ſo faithful, as in plain terms to lay down every Ordinance which God would have us to make the Rule of our obedience. And ſhall we ſuſpect his Maſter would be leſs faithful or deficient? No, in no wiſe.</p>
                     <p>But ſecondly, I did the rather enquire after ſuch a People, becauſe their manner of Adminiſtring of Baptiſm is very clear to me to be moſt conſentaneous to the mind of the Lord Chriſts inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which is by a total immerſion of the Party baptized under water.</p>
                     <p>When I conſulted with the beſt Phylologiſts in the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue, whether Sacred, or Prophane, I found all <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no Ore</hi> profeſs, That <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to dip, or put over head, as the Dyar doth his Cloath into his Liquors, which is confeſſed to be the genuine meaning of the word, even by thoſe who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Adverſaries to the carrying on of Baptiſm by immerſion. Let me give you one inſtead of many, and that an eminent one; it is learned <hi>Spanhemius</hi> in his <hi>Dubia Evangelica, Dub.</hi> 24. <hi>Partis tertiae,
<note place="margin">Thus much the Gent. had in print, which they willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed.</note> ad calcem;</hi> where having diſcuſſed <hi>ex profeſſo, quid</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſignifie, concludes that this expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, to uſe his very terms, <hi>Syncera &amp; conformis ſignificationi verbi, &amp; communi Chriſtianorum, immo omnium Graecè docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum calculo comprobata.</hi> And this ſenſe of the word is received and retained by the learned Tranſlators in the moſt eminent Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages of Weſt Chriſtendome.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> retain the Greek word <hi>Bapte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118147:14"/>
                     <p>The High and Low <hi>Dutch</hi> render it <hi>Doop</hi> and <hi>Tauff,</hi> which ſignifie a total immerſion, and <hi>Eu tauffen,</hi> to baptize, as is well known to thoſe that are knowing and acquainted in theſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</p>
                     <p>Add hereunto the conformity between the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <hi>tebilah</hi> in our Language, which is a total Immerſion, as appears by that expreſſion our Nation gives concerning a Woman going to purifie her ſelf in Water, after the daies of her ſeparation, becauſe of her uncleanneſs, ſhe is ſaid to go <hi>lattevillah,</hi> to be hid over Head and Ears.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall only add this one Teſtimony of our Rabbines, which when I found comformable to the practice of the Diſciples of the Meſſiah in the carrying on of this Ordinance of Baptiſm as it is held forth in the Scriptures by immerſion of the Parties to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, it was of great weight and authority with me, and it is this, <hi>In ſepher Jalkut O nitzachon,</hi> ſet out by <hi>R. Mulhuſino, argel letalmidei talui lalechet litvilah,</hi> it is a cuſtome of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the hanged man (for my Nation in mentioning of Chriſt Periphraſe him by contempt, <hi>talui,</hi> the hang'd man) to go to the place of Immerſion to be hid over head and ears in Water. And thus the Lord having made plain my way before me, and bringing me to a people walking according to the light, which through the Scriptures confirmed, by the Teſtimony both of the learned in my own and other Nations, who was I that I ſhould reſiſt God, and turn away from thoſe, whom God had diſcovered, to my poor wandring ſoul, to be a people walking in the way of his own appointment, and according to thoſe convictions that were upon my ſpirit? For whoſe Communion I do exceedingly bleſs God, and wherein I greatly rejoice. The Lord Chriſt having given into my ſpirit abundance of joy and refreſhing, as a ſignal token of his good liking, and gratious approbation of this my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, warming my heart under the full diſcovery of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made good to me both in the union of my ſoul to himſelf, and giving me into the imbraces of, and communion with his People.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Him that commeth to me, I will in no wiſe cast out,</hi> John 6.37.</p>
                     <p>Now to God onely wiſe, who hath ſhewed me theſe grear
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118147:15"/>things, the God of my Fathers, keeping Covenant for ever, who hath not taken his mercy from me, nor ſuffered his Truth to fail, but hath taken one of the out-caſts of his antient Iſrael, and brought it home to himſelf, To him be glory and Dominion throughout all Ages, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Tamveniſhlam tehillah leel barach. Joſephus Ben Iſrael,</hi> ex Judaeo Chriſtianus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118147:15"/>
                  <head>The Adminiſtrators Animadverſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Declaration and Confeſſion, wherein the glorious Order and Method of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhines forth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IT is obſervable, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt was pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf to this poor ſoul that asked not after him, to advance him as a living Monument of free grace and mercy; like as the Woman of <hi>Sychar,</hi> comming to Jacobs well to draw wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for her bodies comfort, met unexpectedly with a living Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of diſtinguiſhing grace, freely ſtreaming out to her ſoul. So was the Lord pleaſed, while this Jew was pumping the water of Philoſophy, for the accompliſhment of the outward man, to open the glorious Fountain of the Divine Nature, for the bleſſed informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to the great admiration of his Spirit, until that happy ſeaſon blinded with the Traditions of his Fathers. <hi>O the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing love of God!</hi> Rom. 11.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Goſpel-like order of this great work deſerves our moſt ſerious thoughts; that high and wonderful doctrine which the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty laies for a ſure Foundation in his heart, is it whereon eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bleſſedneſs depends.</p>
                  <p>And this is life eternal, <hi>That they might know thee the onely true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> Joh. 17.3.</p>
                  <p>He is firſt awakened (as it were) by <hi>Eſays</hi> Viſion, the diſcovery of that glorious, infinite bleſſed Three in One; Holy Father, <hi>Eſa.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient people the Jews have ever accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it great blaſphemy to call God a Perſon.</note> 6.3. Holy Son, <hi>John</hi> 12.41. Holy Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.26. and other Foundation can no man lay. Wherefore let holy hearts la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a right underſtanding of this excellent myſtery, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7, 13, 20, 21. <hi>Little Children, keep your ſelves from the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of mens vain inventions; let the holy expreſſion of men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired be your rule, without adding or dimiſhing,</hi> Rev. 22.18, 19.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118147:16"/>
                  <p n="3">3. No ſooner hath he conceived with this bleſſed truth, but the grand enemy of the Saints ſtands before him with fearful temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Revelat. 22.4.</note> either to ſtrangle it before, or devour it ſo ſoon as it was born.</p>
                  <p>And this occaſioned thoſe ſharp conflicts in this diſtreſſed <hi>Jew,</hi> who was now put very hard to it; ſo that either he muſt extinguiſh this Candle of the Lord, lighted in his ſoul, and utterly relinquiſh this glorious doctrine of ſalvation; or elſe he muſt forſake all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and enjoyments, and be an exile for ever, from that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent place of his Nativity, which is accounted a ſecond <hi>Eden,</hi> even the choice Garden of the world. Alas poor ſeeming Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, how many of you are entangled in theſe ſnares of relations, and enjoyments, which you dare not, will not relinquiſh for Chriſt, ſo as to make a bold Profeſſion of the deſpiſed Truths of a Crucified Redeemer? O how will you ſtand in judgement with this happy Convert, who hath forſaken all to follow the Lord Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But now behold a ſtumbling-block, ſurpaſſing all Satans temptations, or ſnares of relations, or whatſoever elſe could be as a Mountain obſtructing his paſſage towards <hi>Sion.</hi> This is the ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let coloured Whore, ſitting upon ſeven Hills, that monſtrous ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> whoſe dreadful abhominations, ſtops the advance of this ſeeking ſoul; he concludes theſe cannot be the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that thus wallow in all manner of impiety, whoredom, murder, ſodomy, theft, covetouſneſs, pride, Pontificial Pride, but eſpecially that filthy and deteſtable idolatry of Image and Picture Worſhip, which the juſt God ſo ſeverely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by a 70 years Captivity of his nation in literal Babylon,
<note place="margin">Ez. 23.27.38. Neh. 13.28.</note> with that other ſin of horrible prophanation of the ſolemn time of Gods worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Let every ſincere ſoul that can either pray,
<note place="margin">Jer. 51.3.</note> preach, or bend a Bow, lay out it ſelf to the utmoſt, purſe, perſon, all, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this <hi>Man of ſin</hi> (with his bloody, helliſh <hi>Inquiſition</hi>) that ſo mightily hindereth the great work of <hi>Iſraels</hi> converſion. <hi>O Daughter of Babylon who art to be (waſted) deſtroyed, happy ſhall he be that rewardeth thee as thou hast ſerved us; happy ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth thy little ones againſt the ſtones.</hi> Pſa. 137.8, 9.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. While Romiſh abominations cauſe his retreat towards
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118147:16"/>his former legal profeſſion, his perplexed Soul, (acted by the Spirit of the living God, to pant and breath after him, who hath perfectly fulfilled the Law, by contrary motions and ſtruglings) like <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> in the womb of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> is nigh unto deſpair, even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſplit upon that dreadful Rock.</p>
                  <p>In this mount of ſtraights, the holy one of Iſrael appears, who having laid ſo ſure a foundation in his precious ſoul, carries it on gloriouſly to perfection,
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> making out unto him the next great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Godlineſs, <hi>God manifest in the Fleſh.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> While he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the groſs corruptions of the Jewiſh Doctors, labouring to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure that ſerene Prophecie wherin the glory of this Goſpel Myſtery ſhines forth; the like impiety he diſcovers in their ſenceleſs and groſs abuſe of the Kingly Prophet,
<note place="margin">Iſay 7.14.</note> concerning the ſufferings of Chriſt, which ſerve more to eſtabliſh him in the faith of the Goſpel: So having gotten the New Teſtament of ſome Popiſt Prieſt (the chief benefit he ever received from Papiſts) he finds all prophecies concerning the Incarnation, Paſſion, Reſurrection, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, exactly fulfilled in him, in whom all promiſes are yea and Amen.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Being thus informed of theſe great myſteries of God, he next by reflection upon himſelf, diſcerns firſt, What he was by Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Innocent and happy.</hi> Secondly, What he is (without a Savior) by ſin, <hi>Wretched and miſerable.</hi> Thirdly, What he would be, <hi>Gratious and glorious:</hi> and ſeeing Chriſt the only way to this bleſſedneſs, he is ſo gratiouſly ſtrengthned from on high, as to abandon all enjoyments and earthly comforrs, and to caſt himſelf upon a naked Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Hereupon he ſets upon a diligent ſearch of a Chriſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned in the beautiful converſation of a People profeſſing the Faith of the Goſpel; not after the Traditions and Inventions of men, but according to the exact preſcription of the King of Saints:</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Taking his life in his hand, through dangers and difficulties, he viſits <hi>Germany,</hi> where finding his hopes fruſtrate by <hi>Heſſeu,</hi> he comes to <hi>Hamburg;</hi> and there the gratious hand of Providence brings the Fame of Engliſh Profeſſors to his ear. Oh that the increaſing glory of our Land, may more and more allure the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts of Iſrael, to come to the knowledge and profeſſion of the Son of God; yea let all that profeſs the name of Chriſt, labour to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118147:17"/>adorn the glorious Doctrine of Salvation in this happy Iſle, that they may never crucifie the Son of God afreſh, nor put him to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſhame by their miſcarriages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Curſed be he that maketh the blind to wander out of the way;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 27.18. Mat. 18.7. Eſay 57.14. &amp; 62.10.</note> then woe to <hi>Rome,</hi> the great Mother of Harlots and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; woe to <hi>Germany;</hi> woe to <hi>Heſſen;</hi> yea, woe and alas to Engliſh Profeſſors, (all who call themſelves Chriſtians) that by any corruption in Life or Doctrine ſhall prove a ſtumbling-block to ſuch inquiring, ſeeking ſouls.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>Englands</hi> Renown adds wings to the heightned deſires of this diſtreſſed Rabby, who upon holy reſolutions of this high deſign, is vehemently aſſaulted by Satan (who had not forgot his old lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in <hi>Peter</hi>) ſaying, <hi>Maſter pity thy ſelf; the Engliſh permit not any of thy Nation to abide amongſt them, they have ſlain thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and canſt thou think to eſcape?</hi> But getting victory over this temptation,
<note place="margin">Gen. 12.11, 12, 13.</note> and imbarking for <hi>England,</hi> he is ſuddenly ſurprized by another, (like the Father of the faithful, for the preſervation of his life) even ſlaviſh fear, not knowing of the liberty in <hi>England</hi> to his people, he anſwered to the Mariners, <hi>That he was an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not, I hope, either daub with untempered Morter, to ſow Pillowes under any arm-holes; far be it from me to extenuate any ſin; yet ſomething me-thinks may and ought to be ſpoken in this matter.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it is a received and avowed Principle amongſt the Jews, that nothing is ſin, when life is concerned, except Murder and Idolatry.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That this Jew was not yet throughly inſtructed in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; not any Chriſtians he had met with making Conſcience of ſuch kind of untruths.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It was through the ſame fear that ſurprized <hi>Iacob, David, Peter,</hi> and other dear ſervants of Chriſt, both of old and in our late wars, many a precious ſoul changing his Name, &amp;c. when life was in danger; but this was their infirmity, as it was alſo his, who profeſſeth his ſorrow, and doth hope he hath obtained mercy, upon <hi>Pauls</hi> account, <hi>becauſe he did it ignorantly in unbelief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I would give a word of caution to all the dear ſervants of Chriſt, to abſtain from all appearance of evill, and not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118147:17"/>to commit the leaſt ſin, to avoid the greateſt danger, but walk in Gods path, and leave the ſucceſs to him.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. This hath occaſioned many falſe reports, as that he is no Jew, but a Jeſuit, an Impoſtor, a Counterfeit, and what not? whereas it will evidently appear a Noon-day verity to any ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon that ſhall converſe with him, that he is indeed a Iew; eſpecially when they ſhall behold that manifeſt token in his Fleſh, the diſtinguiſhing Character of Circumciſion, which I alſo ſaw before I baptized him.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. But the mighty power of Faith grounded upon many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, eſpecially this, <hi>All that the Father giveth me ſhall come to me, and him that cometh to me I will in no wiſe cast out,</hi> Iohn. 6.37. bearing him through all theſe great undertakings, for his Names ſake, who made this gracious promiſe his, the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtration of Evangelical Repentance, and a throughly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Nature.</p>
                  <p>The cleer knowledge of the great Myſterie of Godlineſs, the gracious flowings of love from life, and life from light; the ſweet experimental breathings of a Chriſt within (in a more excellent manner than I am able to recite) did even conſtrain me to profeſs, that I have not found a more bleſſed work of Grace, no not in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. And therefore looking upon him as a ſubject fitly qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (through Grace) for Chriſts Kingdom, (my very ſoul cleaving to him, and the ſame in tire affections abundantly flowing from my faithful Fellow-Labourer, with full approbation of all my Brethren that heard him) I called upon him in the words of that holy man, <hi>And now why tarriest thou? ariſe and be baptized,
<note place="margin">Acts 22.16.</note> and waſh away thy ſins, calling on the name of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. Which Initiating Ordinance he being well inform'd in, as to the ſubject matter, <hi>Beleevers,</hi> and the exact manner, <hi>Dipping,</hi> or <hi>Plunging,</hi> both from the holy Scriptures, and from the full teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the moſt learned Jewiſh Doctors, averring, that the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Diſciples of Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> (the Hang'd Man) was to baptiſe their Converts in Rivers, by Immerſion, or Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the whole body under water, according to the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of cleanſing Lepers, and of menſtruous Women, even to this day.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon, after a publike ſolemn Profeſſion of the Lord
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118147:18"/>Jeſus, and humble addreſſes to his Throne for his gracious preſence, ſome hundreds accompanying him to the River <hi>Tyne,</hi> he was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, who return'd him in a rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing frame of ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.49.</note> and hath filled his ſoul ſince with much ſpiritual ſweetneſs.</p>
                  <p>Now let all that are the Lords Remembrancers, give him no reſt untill he bring in all his Antients gloriouſly, and make <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> a Praiſe in the Earth,
<note place="margin">Iſai 24.23. &amp; 62.7 &amp; 60.1.</note> by cauſing that joyful found to ring in their ears,<q rend="inline"> 
                        <hi>Ariſe, ſhine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee.</hi>
                        <bibl>Rom. 11.25, 26.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tho. Tillam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THus I have truly preſented the <hi>Falſe Jew,</hi> the greateſt part whereof was omitted by theſe Gentlemen, and yet they were pleaſed to print my <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon the whole: And when they had ſo done, they offer to the world their <hi>Conſiderations</hi> upon them, telling the judicions Reader, <hi>That he will ſee without their Advertiſement, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>9</label> how theſe Animadverſiens are rather the Iſſues of the Administrators own thoughts, than bottomed upon the Confeſſion: for many things,</hi> ſay they, <hi>he Animadverts upon, are not viſible to us in the Declaration, but ſure he had a mind to make ſomething of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The former part which the Gentlemen have printed, was more properly the Jews confeſſion, and the later part, which they have omitted, was his Declaration. Now they having about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore lines of the later part before their eyes in print, have willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken it off at the end of ſeven lines,
<note place="margin">Caetera deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derantur.</note> telling the world, that the reſt is wanting, and then inſult over my <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> as lame and defective, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>10</label> and the Iſſues of my own thoughts, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to the judicious Reader: which appeal, I alſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make, (now that all is come to his view) let him freely judge whether theſe Gentlemen have abuſed me, by labouring to make my <hi>Animadverſions and my ſelf</hi> equally monſtrous: They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude vvith a Scoff, <hi>But ſure he had a mind to make ſomething of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118147:18"/>
               <p>I think 'tis evident that theſe Gent had a mind to make ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, when they printed not the one half, and yet gave forth my <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon all. But to their conſiderations upon them.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Their firſt Conſideration.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This glorious change which the Administrator was ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of, was in a moneth, by reading ſome books in Lieutenant-Collonel</hi> Hobſons <hi>houſe, as himſelf pretended: How ſoon ſhall a man be called by theſe men, a living Monument of free Grace, though a meer ſtranger onely, upon cloſing with their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply.</hi> Me thinks 'tis harſh that theſe Gentlemen ſhould limit the holy one of Iſrael, and judge it no true work of grace, unleſs it be above a moneth in doing: That <hi>New-England</hi> way of keeping perſons upon trial many Moneths, my ſoul could never cloſe with. The way of Chriſt, is to receive poor, wounded, thirſty, penitent ſouls, upon their earneſt deſires. If theſe Gentlemen would give me one Scripture for rejecting ſuch, (as ſuch this Jew ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) really I ſhall give them thanks, and ſoon change my judgment; but till then, I ſhall endeavour to follow the practice of <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.41.&amp; 8.12, 13. &amp; 16.33. &amp; 18.8.</note> Paul,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> in looking upon thoſe that profeſs the faith of Chriſt, and Repentance, from dead works, as living Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of free Grace, and fit for the Ordinances of the Goſpell. If they ſhall prove hypocrites, as <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.6.</note> and the <hi>falſe Jew</hi> did, we have in a readineſs to revenge all ſuch diſobedience.</p>
                  <p>But whereas the Gentlemen preſent us to the world, as owning ſuch <hi>for living Monuments of free grace,</hi> that do but only cloſe with our opinion, it is a great Untruth: we do well know, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>11</label> that few or none deſire communion with us, but ſuch as are convinced of Diſciples Baptiſm onely: and therefore it is the leaſt matter we ſeek after; our main buſineſs is to labour (as far as the Rule leads us) to find their faith firm, their repentance right, a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meaſure of knowledge, and ſelf-denial, their converſation holy (ſince the time they were enlightned) and by theſe fruits, we judge them that deſire fellowſhip with us,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.16. Gal. 5.22.</note> to have paſſed through the pangs of the New Birth, and ſubjects fit for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; and hereupon we ſhew them all the Forms and Ordinances of the Temple, the out-goings, and in-commings, and ſo open
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118147:19"/>the armes of our deareſt affections to embrace them. But it is well known, that divers Perſons under full convictions, as to our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as theſe Gent. term it, have been denyed communion with us, and deſired to wait in the uſe of means, until the fruits fore mentioned ſhall appear, whereas theſe Gent. do own and receive ſuch in whom neither Faith, Repentance, Self-denial, Knowledge, or deſire at all appears.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Their ſecond Conſideration.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the Administrator calls the diſtinction of Perſons, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols; as at a meeting in</hi> Newcaſtle <hi>the laſt year, he called them appearances, and manifestations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply.</hi> Theſe Gent. have no leſs abuſed me in this, than in their High Commiſſion-like dealing in that Conference at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> would rigidly impoſe the term Perſon upon me, and when I put him to produce one rule for it, which by Scripture he could not, he demanded what I would call the Three Perſons? My anſwer was, that I durſt not give any Appellation at all, but Father, Son, and Spirit, God being gratiouſly pleaſed ſo to appear or manifeſt himſelf to us, when ſuddainly he ſtopped my ſpeech, and ſpake very loud to the people, that I called God an appearance, or a manifeſtation, which went for currant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt that party. And the like height of ſpirit was ſeen in the ſame Gent. when I was ſpeaking of God as a Father, a Son, a Spirit; he preſently riſeth up, crying, <hi>A Son, a Son, is that Scripture Language?</hi> Then caſting his arms abroad to the people, <hi>Look ye friends</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>this is the Gent. that stands ſo much for Scripture, and now he ſaies, A Son, a Son;</hi> then turning to me he ſaid, <hi>I muſt call him the Son,</hi> I anſwered, <hi>A Son;</hi> and he hotly replyed often, <hi>the Son, not a Son, tis no Scripture phraſe;</hi> till at laſt he ſate down ſilent, upon my rehearſall of this Scripture, <hi>To us a Child is born, to us a Son is given.</hi> Such hath been the carriage of ſome of theſe Gent. towards me, more like the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prelates, than humble Goſpel Miniſters. But concerning the great charge, <hi>of calling the diſtinctions of Perſons Idols,</hi> I have indeed warned Chriſtians, to keep themſelves from the Idols of mens vains inventions;
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9. Pſal 99.8.</note> becauſe Chriſt hath declared it to be vain worſhip; and tis that which procures the vengeance of God upon it. Now if the Appellation, Perſon, be not Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, tis a meer invention of Man, and ſo an Idol. <hi>Yes</hi> (ſay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118147:19"/>they) <hi>we have the Author to the</hi> Hebrews, <hi>and is not he of more Authority than all the Rabbies in the World? Reply,</hi> Undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly he is; for however ſome do queſtion the Authority of this Epiſtle, yet I do firmly embrace it, as the very word of Chriſt. But the Author of this Epiſtle doth not call God a Perſon; the words quoted by the Gen. are theſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the expreſs character of his ſubſtance, or ſubſiſtence. Theſe Gent. tell the world of the Adminiſtrators non-acquaintance with the Rabbies: and that I do not diſprove them, I ſhall onely at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent make uſe of our own Writers,
<note place="margin">Crit. Sac. pag. 272.</note> who poſſibly may help to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſome of them, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (though it be tranſlated) <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> for a Perſon, and that ſome render it <hi>Eſſence,</hi> others <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> others <hi>Subſistence;</hi> yet all theſe are improper, and that the proper ſignification of this word, is a <hi>Foundation,</hi> or <hi>Baſis,</hi> which ſubſiſting of it ſelf bears up other things: In 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4. it is <hi>Confidence.</hi> In <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. it is <hi>Exiſtence.</hi> In the Scripture it doth ſignifie, <hi>A firm and ſettled perſwaſion of the mind upon any thing;</hi> mark it well, this is the Scripture ſignification of the word; but, ſaith he, <hi>It is alſo uſed</hi> (obſerve, it is alſo uſed) <hi>for the Divine eſſence with a Perſonal propriety, Heb.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee this worthy Author layeth no ſuch weight upon the word perſon, as theſe Gent do; to charge a man with deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trinity, that cannot own the term. Let us a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another learned Writer,
<note place="margin">Gheynell Div. Trinun. p. 22.</note> who was commended to me with ſeeming affection by Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who indifferently accepts the word <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Subſistence,</hi> and plainly ſaies, <hi>that the word,</hi> which they tranſlate <hi>Perſon, is Subſiſtence,</hi> Heb. 1, 3.
<note place="margin">Page 81.</note> and in page 84. the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which we render. <hi>Subſistence,</hi> and by way of Analogy, <hi>Perſon,</hi> obſerve, it is by way of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, he further holds forth,
<note place="margin">Page 89</note> that the Fathers did uſe the phraſe of three Hypoſtaſes, not daring it ſeems, in the pureſt Primitive times, to tranſlate it <hi>Perſon,</hi> but at laſt,
<note place="margin">Page 91.</note> they took the boldneſs to uſe the word <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I deſire to be informed why this word <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> which the Primitive Fathers ſo long uſed, may not ſtill be kept without tranſlation, as well as other
<note n="*" place="margin">As Thylacce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Mat. 23 5. Anathema Meranath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> words, whoſe proper ſignification cannot eaſily be rendred in Engliſh. But to proceed with Maſter <hi>Cheynell,</hi> pag. 89, 90. you have this ſober Chriſtian concluſion, <hi>We are prompted by the Spirit to explain this Myſtery thus, the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118147:20"/>Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, are three in ſubſistence, but one in nature; no Myſtery can be explained with leſs violence, and more ſobriety; for we are preciſe in keeping to the very words of Scripture, in explaining this Grand Mystery to the plaineſt of men; and therefore they were ſentenced of old, that did not believe this plain truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I am ſentenced now for profeſſing the truth; for when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared my judgement in this glorious Three in One, nothing would ſerve their turn but the very word <hi>Perſon;</hi> what the height of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was God knows.</p>
                  <p>One obſervation more I ſhall add from Mr. <hi>Cheynell</hi> upon <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin;</hi> Non minori Religione, &amp;c. <hi>Whatever we think or ſpeak of our own heads concerning God, will be like our ſelves, unſavory, fooliſh and vain</hi> (and yet theſe Gent. are troubled that their inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted word <hi>Perſon</hi> ſhould be tearmed an Idol) <hi>no Language is rich enough, no words are ſignificant enough to declare this profound Myſtery, which the underſtanding of Men and Angels cannot comprehend, nor the tongue of Men and Angels expreſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore I hope, that untill theſe Gentlemen can ſhew me the word <hi>Perſon</hi> in the Scripture, I ſhall enjoy my Chriſtan liberty to adore the eternal Father, Son, and Spirit, according to Chriſts Word, and not after the inventions and rigid injunctions of men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are three that bear record in Heaven,
<note place="margin">1 John 5.7.</note> the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Little Children</hi> (I warn you again) <hi>keep your ſelves from Idols, Amen.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 21.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Gent. have prevented me, in anſwering themſelves, how I came to know that the Jews <hi>count it great blaſphemy to call God a Perſon;</hi> for they preſently conclude, <hi>That I had it from this Counterfeit</hi> Jew: and truly in this they are right. I ſhould hope for ſome Chriſtian accomodation, if I could find theſe Gen. as ingenuous, in acknowledging they have done me wrong in taking this Note out of the Margin (where I wrote it) and putting it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Text, or body of my Animadverſions; poſſibly God may give them Eyes to ſee the many unbrotherly, light, unſavory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and carriage in their falſe <hi>Jew:</hi> Amongſt the reſt, me thinks their third conſideration is no ſolid one, <hi>viz. You ſee by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118147:20"/>this time how the Candle ſmells; Is not this to call darkneſſe light?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am perſwaded, if I had written of ſeeing the Candle ſmell, theſe Gent. would have made themſelſes as merry with it, as they have done with their dear Friend in their Narrative. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, they demand, <hi>If my Animadverſions upon the Jews Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, be not to call darkneſs light?</hi> To which I muſt return, That his affliction, according to his Declaration, was as truely light to me, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> believing was to <hi>Philip,</hi> Acts 8.13. And I ſhall leave to the Saints to judge, whether my charitable concluſion of the Jews trembling, melting confeſſion, have not more Goſpel-like light, than theſe Gentlemens following Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, which by way of Quaere, they ſend out into the world thus; <hi>Whether by this rayling at Rome there may not be hopes of the Adminiſtrators reall turning from Popery, which we much ſuſpected by his ſpeedy and cordiall cloſing with the counterfeit Jew.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> That which theſe Gentlemen term <hi>railing at Rome,</hi> is the expreſs Language of Gods Spirit; there are very few words in my fourth Section, but what the Scripture breaths againſt <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> and as for the Quaery, I muſt acknowledge (it is ſo full of envy) that it puts my ſpirit out of frame, ſomething (but I fear it is a temptation) moves me to anſwer in another manner, but let the Prophet anſwer for me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then, ſaid they, come,
<note place="margin">Jer. 18.18, 19. &amp; 20.10.</note> and let us deviſe devices againſt</hi> Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah; <hi>Come, and let us ſmite him with the tongue. Give heed to me, O Lord, for I heard the defaming of many, fear on every ſide; Report, ſay they, and we will report it: all my familiars watched for my halting,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Father forgive</hi> (theſe poor preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced Gent.) <hi>for they know not what they do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To their fifth Conſideration, I have already replyed in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to my third, concerning the light I judged the Jews eſtate by. And whereas they tell the Reader, that he cannot but <hi>ſee my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in heart work;</hi> let me alſo tell the Reader, that if all be true which theſe Gent. affirm of me, they have as little skill in heart work as I; for ſome of them (if not all) reported of me, as a godly, able, and approved Preacher of the Goſpel; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon importuned me to Preach the Lecture at <hi>Hexham,</hi> as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me utterly averſe to any engagement in a Pariſh way: Yea one
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118147:21"/>of theſe Gent. (not long ſince) profeſſed, that he believed I had grace; and yet now they have ſubſcribed it, that they ſuſpect my being a Papiſt ſtill; they bewail the ſadneſs of my condition, as one given up of God to believe lies, They proclaim me igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the great my ſteries of the Goſpel, and heart work; really if theſe things be ſo, theſe Gent. are as ignorant in heart work as my ſelf; but if they be not ſo, what manifeſt wrong have they done in publiſhing theſe to the world?</p>
                  <p>And whereas in their ſixth Conſideration, they mind me, <hi>That the falſe Jew often profeſſed that he had no work of Grace before his arrival in England: and then deſire to know, how I diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that his perplexed ſoul was acted by the Spirit of the living God, to pant and breath after Jeſus Chriſt, and to abandon all enjoyments for him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> He had no work of Grace indeed, neither before, nor after his arrival; but he ſeemed to me to have: and theſe Gent. themſelves have no other way to know a work of grace, but by the fruits; both they and we muſt be contented with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Samuel,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.7. 1 Cor. 13 9.12.</note> Peter, Philip, Paul,</hi> and other Saints, who can know but in part, ſee through a glaſs darkly; it is Gods Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royal, to know and ſearch the heart: ſo that the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be, nor whether this, or any other Hypocrite do pant af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or forſake all for Chriſt; but whether an Elect Veſſel may do ſo, before he ſee his intereſt in Chriſt. I hope I have ſo much acquaintance with heart work in my ſelf, and many others, as to know that a pretious ſoul may pant and breath many a day, moneth, and year, ſeeking fot a Chriſt without (to uſe the Jewes language) before they find or feel on dragm of comfort of the leaſt knowledge of a Chriſt within. How many drooping, diſconfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, broken, trembling hearts are there, wraſtling with many violent aſſaults, terrified under many dreadful temptations, ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling through the pangs and bitter throwes of the New Birth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt be formed in them? What would ſuch poor ſouls give, nay, what would they not give for one glimpſe of his reconciled face, one beam of light from his glorious countenance, one ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raviſhing embrace from their Beloved, before they feel him (like his firſt Goſpel Meſſenger) ſpringing in the Womb for joy? who all this while keeps behind a thick and dark cloud, on purpoſe to make ſincere ſouls more earneſtly and affectionately ſeek and cry
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118147:21"/>after him; for he loves to ſee their Face, and hear their Voice, even while they are in the ſecret places of the ſtaires; yea, poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, whilſt they lye proſtrate at his feet, begging his favour;
<note place="margin">Caut. 2.14.</note> they meet onely with frowns, denying, rejecting, it may be ſpurning his poor Petitioners, as dogs from his preſence, who are willing to be ſo accounted, if they may obtain ſome of his crumbs from under his Table,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.22 Pſal. 48.10.</note> the meaneſt Ordinances of his Houſe (ſlighted by wantons) which yet their dejected ſouls eſteem too precious for them; yea, ſo baſe, ſo vile, ſo abominable and filthy in their own eyes are they, that crying out undone, unclean, polluted, duſt and aſhes, wretched creatures, death, flaſhings of Hell Fire, walking upon the brink of that dreadfull Praecipice which deſcends unto the ſoul-ſwallowing Gulf of deſpair; till at length a ſtill and ſoft Voice, ſome ſweet heavenly whiſpers, <hi>He ſhew thee the kindneſs of God, thou poor dead dog,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 9.3.8.11. Pſal. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ult.</note> thou miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, polluted, dunghill-wretch; O thou afflicted ſoul, thou toſſed troubled ſoul, what wilt thou? be it unto thee even as thou wilt:</hi> and then (ſometimes) <hi>Or ever I was aware,
<note place="margin">Cant. 6.11.</note> my ſoul made me like the Chariots of Aminadib</hi> (ſaith the poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Saint.) And truly ſuch like was the Jews condition to me, and many more diſcerning Spirits who heard him ſpeak (farre beyond all that hath been Printed by him, or of him) as one who was brought out of Egyptian darkneſſe, and had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled hard, through the howling and terrible Wilderneſs of great afflictions, before he found that he had got one ſtep into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed poſſeſſion, any intereſt at all in Chriſt, onely ſeeking a Chriſt without; ſo exquiſitely could he act the Hypocrite, in all the motions and methods of a work of grace. And whereas the Gentlemen deſire to know <hi>by what Principle he did it?</hi> I muſt tell them, from a Principle infuſed by the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, transforming himſelf into an Angel of light, the way of all Hypocrites. I hope theſe Gentlemen know, that Hypocrites may, and do abandon all enjoyments, and expoſe themſelves to all dangers, and miſeries, as they think, for Chriſt, or elſe, what ſhall we think of many of thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and their Fathers the <hi>Franciſcan Fryars,</hi> who have undoubtedly begun the work, by ſome ſuch Impoſtors as our Jew, who forſake all, and macerate their bodies, though as yet, I think, they are not come to whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and other Penance; I may not queſtion, but <hi>Iudas</hi> had
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118147:22"/>forſaken all, as well as <hi>Peter;</hi> neither could theſe Gent. have been able to diſcern whether would prove the Traytor, any more than their dear friend or I could diſcern the Jew would prove an Hypocrite.</p>
                  <p>And now if the enlightned Saint (conſidering what hath been offered) ſhall obſerve the Gents. concluſion of this their ſixth Conſideration, <hi>viz. By this time you know both the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strator and his Diſciple;</hi> he may eaſily conclude by what Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple they ſpeak it; but I ſhall leave them to God, beſeeching him to pitty and pardon them.</p>
                  <p>The Genr. paſſing by my ſeventh and eight Section to avoid prolixity (as they ſay) being deſirous onely to <hi>point out my groſſer miſtakes;</hi> They declare in their ninth Conſideration, their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>That I ſhould compare the Jew to the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo harden him in his ſins:</hi> To which I reply, That it was upon his profeſſed ſorrow for his lies, that I pleaded for him; but after I diſcovered his impoſture, I was as farre from juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, or mincing his ſinnes, as from daubing with untempered Morter, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">un∣truth. </seg>12</label> or my own reaſon. What the Gent. glance at betwixt their ninth and tenth Conſideration, I have already ſpoken to, except this one particular upon my ſecond reaſon, <hi>That I abuſe many gratious Saints which the Jew met with, before he came to Lieutenant Collonel</hi> Hobſon, <hi>charging them with making no conſcience of lyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Far be it from me to charge any one gratious Saint with ſuch abominations. I ſhall deſire the Reader to review my ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> pag. 9. which is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That this Iew was not yet throughly inſtructed in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, not any Chriſtians he had met with making Conſcience of ſuch kind of untrnths.</hi> Now what charge is this?</p>
                  <p>I enquired diligently of the Jew, what Chriſtians he had met with, before he came to the Lieutenant Collonel: he told me <hi>He had onely been with Mr.</hi> Durant <hi>at New-castle, but ſtayed not, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>1</label> for want of entertainment.</hi> And for this Gent. when I ſhall ſee him humbled for that groſſe untruth mentioned pag. 3 I may look upon him as a <hi>gratious Saint.</hi> Now I deſire theſe Gent. to name one gratious Saint that I have perfectly abuſed, by charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to make no conſcience of lyes; if they cannot, then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they have perfectly abuſed me, whom they have ſometimes owned as a gratious Saint.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118147:22"/>
                  <p>But I proceed to their tenth Conſideration, wherein they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That the reports, I called falſe, are now evident truths; and wonder that my confidence ſhould ſwell ſo bigge, upon no better grounds, than by the Narrative.</hi> To which I reply, my grounds were good, I walked by an exact rule which will bear me out.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.4.7.</note> I might better enquire what ſhould ſwell the confidence of theſe Gent, to publiſh ſuch things as they have done for Truths againſt me, from the alone teſtimony of a known lyar, which are notoriouſly falſe?</p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>they lament my condition,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ 2.1.</note> and the whole Society with me in Communion, as given up of God to believe lies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let them conſider well, that whatſoever dirt and filth they caſt in our faces, lights in the Face of the Apoſtles, and primitive Chriſtians, who were frequently deceived by Hypocrites, yet never blamed for admitting them (upon their profeſſion) let theſe Gent. produce one example for ſuch kind of dealing as theirs is with me.</p>
                  <p>But ſecondly, I ſhall deſire the Reader (if he have any light) to conſider ſeriouſly, whether ſtrong deluſions to believe lyes, be a juſt judgement from God upon theſe Gent. or upon us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Jew came to us with moſt exquiſite hypocriſie, in a melting, trembling, weeping frame of ſpirit: all his carriage holy and humble before his Baptiſm; his lyes were unknown to us, till afterward, and then we denyed him communion with us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But after he is known to be a notorious lyar, theſe Gent. have ſo far believed all his relations, that might any way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame us, that without further enquiry, though we are but ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen miles from them, they have publiſhed them all to the world: Is this like the miniſters of Chriſt? Is this to ſpeak and write as the Oracles of God? The Oracle of God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not receive, or raiſe a falſe report,</hi> Exod. 23.1. but theſe Gent. have done both. The Oracle of God ſaith, <hi>Receive not an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt an Elder, but before,</hi> or under, <hi>two or three Witneſſes.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.19. but one ſingle Teſtimony, and that of a known lyar too, hath ſet theſe Gents. Pens a work, to reproach and defame both an Elder, and a whole Church. This Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was urged ſome moneths ſince, by one of theſe gent. who having done me manifeſt injury, in a Publique way of perſecution, I wrote to Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> whom I judged more moderate,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118147:23"/>to deal with him about it: Whereupon the Gent. wrote to me, flatly denying the injury, within theſe fair expreſſions, <hi>I expect a Brotherly ſatisfaction from you, which is firſt, a ſenſe of your over credulity, and unloving readineſs, in believing ill of your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, contrary to</hi> 1 Tim. 5.19. <hi>Secondly, your irregular decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this offence to another.</hi> To which I anſwered, <hi>That I am able to make good the charge by ſufficient witneſſes</hi> (no Jewes) <hi>whenſoever he pleaſeth. Secondly, It was a very publique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and therefore I dealt not irregularly.</hi> But what brotherly ſatisfaction can theſe Gent. make for <hi>their over credulity, and unloving readineſs,</hi> in believing ill of him they term a Brother, from the hand of one Witneſs, whom they know to be an Impoſtor full of Falſhood, and <hi>irregularly</hi> declaring all to the World? which they can never make good. They can never make good, <hi>That I knew of the many plotted lies of the falſe Jew, before I baptized him.</hi> They can never make it good, <hi>That I called the Jew to the Lords Supper, and he refuſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Gent. ſhall reply, <hi>That the falſe Iew told them ſo, and thereupon they publiſh it;</hi> Hath not God ſent them <hi>ſtrong deluſions to believe lies?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They can never make it good, <hi>That I neglected to preach the fundamental truths of the everlasting Goſpel; and made it my buſineſs to preach up Baptiſm ever ſince I came to</hi> Hexham.</p>
                  <p>They cannot make it good, <hi>That we own Perſons, as living monuments of free grace, only upon cloſing with our opinion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They cannot make it good, <hi>That I have charged many gratious Saints, with making no conſcience of lies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe, and other groſs Untruths of theſe Gent. being conſidered, I ſuppoſe I have more cauſe to bewail their ſad condition, as being given up of God to believe, to make, and to publiſh lies; ſo that their own Pen drops their own doom,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11.</note> both in their Title Page, and the cloſure of their tenth Conſideration. But time and occaſions call to a Concluſion: And therefore to their eleventh Conſideration, enquiring, <hi>Whether the work upon my heart, be any better than the Jews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have already anſwered That if it be not, their skil in heart work is as little as they ſay mine is, ſeeing they have judged me truly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. Their 12 Conſideration, I ſhall leave to my beloved Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and faithful Fellow-labourer, to which he anſwers, That the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118147:23"/>twelfth Conſideration hath as much of the Serpent in it, as any of the former. For whereas they mention his preſent ſtation, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends it to be inſerted by them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either to his diſparagement (which is the grand deſign car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on through the falſe Jewiſh Pamphlet) and if ſo, he muſt tell the Gent. it is their weakneſs ſo to judge, they not knowing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they affirm. For as the Office relates to a perſon of no mean qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but one eminent and honorable in his Country, ſo alſo it is a place of conſiderable credit, and no mean truſt, though they would preſent it to the world as deſpicable.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſecondly, If they inſiſt upon his Office as an impediment, ſo that <hi>he cannot labour in the Lords work;</hi> this miſtake is equal with the former. For his Office does not like their fat Lots at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> (for which they take occaſion in their firſt Epiſtle to give <hi>God thanks,</hi> pag. 2. l. 23.) make him ſo corpulent or unwiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but he can once or twice a fortnight lanch out to preach the Goſpel in the dark parts neer adjacent, where are divers Pariſh meeting-houſes, which ſtand as ſo many dark Lanthorns, and which theſe Gents. preſent pomp and greatneſs will not vouchſafe them to viſit, no not once in a Summer, to hold forth their light to ſome thouſands of poor ſouls which ſit in darkneſs, and may, for all them, periſh without underſtanding.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed. As for his great change which theſe Gent. charge him <hi>lately to have profeſſed;</hi> He doubts not, but in the day of the Lord Jeſus his appearing, it ſhall appear that he poſſeſſes what he hath profeſſed. And that it is of a former date, than ſince their Bugbear Articles of Scandals, which they ſay were ſhown him, though he never got a ſight of them to peruſe them, wherein what was of truth, he neither then did, nor will deny. But what he then granted, had it amounted to a Charge, he makes no queſtion but he ſhould have heard of them long ere now; he having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in two Publique Diſputes with the Adminiſtrator, againſt them at <hi>Newcastle,</hi> even before the expiring of their Commiſſion. So that concerning theſe Articles, he hath ground to conclude, That either there was ſelf-conviction upon theſe Gent. that they were falſe, or their proof ſhrunk in and ſailed them, being aſhamed to juſtify ſuch untruths; or there hath been corruptneſs on ſome hands, ſince that a buſineſs, which the world muſt be made believe was ſo wicked, hath been neer upon 3 years pocketed up in ſilence; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118147:24"/>if a truth, hath bin withholden in unrighteouſnes. Any of theſe being granted, which the impartial Reader in reaſon can't deny, there was doubtleſs no ſuch neceſſity, as theſe Gent. pretend, for him to ſtrike in with the Adminiſtrator and his way, (who came not into theſe parts for many moneths after) to ſecure him from the ſtroke of theſe Gent. Mock-Articles of Scandals, they having had time, will and power ſufficient, had they but had ſufficiency of truth and integrity, to have drawn up a charge againſt him. But by the way, let the Reader take notice, that the Adminiſtrator, and his way, holds a rod over theſe Gent. and teaches them moderation. He was ſtruck in with the Adminiſtrator and his way, therefore theſe Gent. waved their Articles. Doth not ſuch an inference well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Gent. that profeſs to be valiant for the Truth upon the Earth?</p>
                  <p>Oh bleſſed be our God, who hath raiſed up ſuch Profeſſors of the Adminiſtrators way, as have chained up men of perſecuting Prelatical ſpirits, ſo that they cannot act up to the height of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief againſt the truths of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Profeſſors of them, as they would.</p>
                  <p>But ſay the Gent. <hi>We deſire to ſee further, &amp;c. Anſ.</hi> They have their deſire, but upon this condition, That he may prevail with them for the like liberty, before he lay the weight of infallibility in a work of grace, upon any, or all their judgements, ſince that experience (whereof ſundry inſtances may be given) hath taught him that theſe Gentlemen are not acted by an infallible ſpirit, but are men ſubject to the like Paſſions, Deluſions, and Miſtakes, as he is.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Optimus ille</l>
                     <l>Qui minimis urgetur.—</l>
                     <bibl>S. A.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>As to their laſt Conſideration, the Adminiſtrator can, through mercy, cheerfully bear all the affronts, deriſions end abuſes of it, and all the reſt; though temptations have not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to anſwer theſe Gent.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17, 18, 19.</note> in another way; but Chriſt hath taught me better, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.23, ſo that when they ſay, <hi>I ſpeak in the ſame Language which the spirit of Satan breathed out of the mouth of my Dear Brother the Counterfeit,</hi> I can patiently bear it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.25.</note> and leave it to the Lord, who was tearmed <hi>Beelzebub</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118147:24"/>before me, and told me what I ſhould meet with. But whereas the Gent. confidently tell their Reader, <hi>That the Counterfeit could never diſſemble ſo handſomely in the Ordinance of Prayer:</hi> (and thereupon deride me thus; <hi>Yet this is the Saint that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator ſaies, he had not found the like, no not in</hi> England.) Let me tell the Reader, what I ſhall punctually prove, whenſoever I am called to it, That this is another groſs untruth, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋntruth. </seg>13</label> and a farther evidence, that the judgement which the Gent. ſay is fallen upon us, hath manifeſtly ſeized upon themſelves, namely, <hi>To be given up of God to believe lyes.</hi> Really Chriſtian Reader this wretched Impoſtor, whom theſe Gent. ſay at adventure, could not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo handſomely in the Ordinance of Prayer, could ſpeak ſweetly, ſoundly, affectionately, feelingly in Prayer, ſo as to draw forth the heart exceedingly, of ſuch as are richly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in the things of Chriſt. But it is manifeſt how readily, yea, and greedily the Gentlemen embrace whatſoever the falſe Jew ſpeaks, that may any way wound us; wheras all other things that ſeem to appear for us, they brand as Lyes, Forgeries, Deceits, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Gent. cloſe, leaving the Adminiſtrator upon the Stage, in his relation of the falſe Jews joy, and ſpiritual ſweetneſs after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and they affirm, its true, <hi>He was obſerved to ſmile as he came out of the water,</hi> and being asked the reaſon why he ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it was as eaſily believed, as ſpoken by him, <hi>to be the joy of the Holy Ghost.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And I ſhall conclude alſo with declaring, That I am certain theſe Gentlemen themſelves, are no other way able to diſcern, or know, where the joy of the Holy Ghoſt, and Heavenly incomes are, but by the expreſſions and actions of the party, which were not wanting in this exquiſite Hypocrite. As for his ſmiling as he came out of the Water, it is as eaſily believed by theſe Gentlemen it ſeems as ſpoken, to uſe their own words. But I perceive theſe Gentlemen little know what it is to be buried in Baptiſm, that can believe a Perſon baptized, is ſo ſuddenly in a ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling condition: I was as neer to him, as any, and helping him out of the Water, I heard him pray, as ſoon as he could take breath.</p>
                  <p>I leave all to the Lord and his Saints, it is their work to judge the World; let them judge between us whether is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118147:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118147:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118147:26"/>guilty of believing Lyes, as eaſily as ſpoken, We in giving credit to the falſe Jews holy, humble Confeſſion, when he appeared to us to be adorned with the pure Robes of Snow-white innocence, no guilt at all: or theſe Gent. in embracing whatſoever he told them againſt us, after his notorious falſhood was detected, and they knew him to be an abhominable Lyar?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgest doeſt the ſame things.</hi> Rom. 2.1.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
